<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The godly garden of Gethsemani furnished with holsome fruites of meditation and prayer, vpon the blessed passion of Christ our Redeemer.</title>
            <author>Loarte, Gaspar.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 145 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16645.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120872</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856065</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856065</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21583</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06155)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21583)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 644:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The godly garden of Gethsemani furnished with holsome fruites of meditation and prayer, vpon the blessed passion of Christ our Redeemer.</title>
                  <author>Loarte, Gaspar.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[288] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[W. Carter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1580]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: Loarte, Gaspar.  The godlie garden of Gethsemani.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut illustrations throughout.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 11803a.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11803a on UMI microfilm reel 644.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-S.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Passion --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21583:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21583:1"/>
            <p>The godly garden of GETHSEMANI, furniſhed with holſome fruites of Meditation and prayer, vpon the bleſſed paſſion of Chriſt our Redéemer.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>SVRSVM.</head>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>CANT. I.</bibl>
               <l>Faſciculus Myrrhae dilectus meus mihi:</l>
               <l>inter vbera mea commorabitur.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>A noſegay of myrrh is my true loue to me:</l>
               <l>Betvvene my breſtes his dvvelling shalbe.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:21583:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of crucifixion of Christ</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21583:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y chaunce hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peninge vppon this litle Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe written in the Italian by a deuoute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as it appeareth, and one ſpecially profeſſed by rules of Chriſtian life, to the glorious name of Ieſu: for my ſmall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in that tongue, and further exerciſe therein, I put on it an Engliſh habite of ſuche courſe weauing as ſkil ſerued me. And finding therein ſuche ſwéetenes as is alwayes proper to ſo good matter, I thought good
<pb facs="tcp:21583:3"/>
to beſtowe my ſimple trauayle though with more charges, in preſenting onely the ſame to a ſpeciall good friend or two: as a winter flowre to weare in their boſome, or red Roſe nowe at Chriſtmas, by my tenure or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice due: whiche they might at their pleaſure ioyne with other poſies of their accuſtomed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions. If thou, good Reader, chaunce vpon any one booke tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the liberalitie of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or otherwiſe by more num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber printed then I purpoſed, I haue therefore to deſire thée to accept it with good will, as I know they do to whom of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb facs="tcp:21583:3"/>
I vowed my trauels, &amp; alſo that thou wilt excuſe and beare with all the faultes committed by the Printer or me for this time, which are not ſo great to fruſtrate thée or me of the fruite of thy exerciſe or expectation herein, which is encreaſe of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and deuotion. Of which thou mayſt aſſure thy ſelf to reape as much fruit to thy comfort as is poſſible of ſo litle a treatiſe.</p>
            <p>I haue called it by the name of the garden of <hi>Gethſemani,</hi> allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in my fanſie to the Garden where Chriſte prayed and ſhed both water and blood for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: which name for néede
<pb facs="tcp:21583:4"/>
may put thée ſometime in mind oftner to reſorte to this garden of exerciſe, and to haue Chriſtes wordes to his Diſciples there alwayes ſounding in thy eares &amp; ſlumbring minde: <hi>Can ye not watch with me a litle while?</hi> &amp;c. Alſo our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly <hi>Salomon</hi> and Sauiour Chriſte inuiteth his ſpouſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church in theſe words: <hi>Come into my garden my ſiſter and wife:</hi> And ſhe our mother founde no flowre or fruite in this paradiſe of god more to hir liking, than this trée of life, the bleſſed croſſe of Chriſt: as may wel appeare by hir own words: <hi>A noſegay of myrrhe is my true
<pb facs="tcp:21583:4"/>
loue to me, and within my breſt his habitation ſhal be.</hi> Meaning by the myrrhe, whiche for the bitterneſſe thereof was geuen Chriſt to drinke in his extreme thirſt, and which for the ſwéete ſmell agayne, ſerued amongeſt other thinges to annoynt his body in the ſepulchre: That ſhe reioyced in nothing more then to gather hir ſelfe a poſie of the bitter paynes and ſorowes that Chriſte ſuffered for hir and hir faythfull children. Then accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to hir example, as children rightly nurtured in hir lappe, let vs not thinke it tedious to followe hir courſe and ſteppes,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:5"/>
and ſay with her: <hi>In the ſweete ſent of thy oyntmentes</hi> (Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord) <hi>I do runne after thee.</hi> And let vs holde alwaies in our breaſt, and kéepe in memory by continuall meditation, all the grieuous tormentes and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles which our ſauiour ſuffered for the redemption of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, that therby we may learne and knowe the length &amp; the breadth, the height &amp; depth of that moſte healthfull trée and Croſſe of Chriſt, which of his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy I beſéeche him graunt both thée &amp; me good Reader.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:21583:5"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the fruite of ſuche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout meditation, and of the maner and order of this litle Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man can haue, one of the moſt fruitefull and moſt acceptable to God is, to be often and deuoutely occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, in calling to remembrance and well to conſider in minde (which otherwiſe we terme to meditate) the paſſion of Chriſt our redéemer. The which all the Doctours that write thereof af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:6"/>
and alſo reaſon and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience do playnely declare the ſame. For by ſuch holy medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the ſoule is inflamed in the loue of Chriſt, conſidering howe tenderly he loued it, how muche he ſuffered to ſaue and beautifie it: and moreouer it feareth and is aſhamed of his ſinfulneſſe, knowing &amp; ſéeing how grieuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly it was puniſhed in the ſonne of God, who as the Prophet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay ſaith, was ſtroken of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the ſinnes of his people. Yea the ſoule thereby receiueth in hir ſelfe and increaſeth newe and freſhe deſires to amende the life: ſéeing the liuely and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous
<pb facs="tcp:21583:6"/>
examples which parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly do ſhine in the holy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt. And likewiſe it is thereby ſtyrred and pricked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde to geue thankes &amp; prayſe for his infinite goodneſſe and mercy, that it hath pleaſed him with ſo tender loue to be made a ſacrifice, and to ſuffer ſo bitter death, that he might geue vs miſerable and wretched wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, life and ſaluation. And thus finally the ſoule may ſéeme in ſome parte to pay the great debt it is bounde in, féeling in it ſelfe the great benefite it hath receiued, when it calleth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce and bethinketh
<pb facs="tcp:21583:7"/>
particularly the manyfolde ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, iniuries, and tormentes which the ſauiour of the worlde ſuffred in his death and paſſion: and doth know that this ſeruice is moſt acceptable to him, and alſo is ſory for them who do not the like, but forget the great kindnes of their Redéemer.</p>
               <p>So then, for this and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruits gathered of this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed meditation, certayne Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours affirme that thoſe gayne more, which euery day do medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate with deuotion, ſome little part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſion of Chriſt, than if they ſhould exerciſe manye prayers, faſtings, diſciplins and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:7"/>
chaſtenings of the body other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. And therefore albeit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue copiouſly at large writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hereof, yet notwithſtanding for the better commoditie and helpe of them that haue not ſuch bookes, &amp; ſpecially for ſuche our Chriſtian brothers and ſiſters ſakes, that haue a deſire to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe them ſelues in the meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the paſſion of our Lorde, we are moued to finde out ſome meanes howe they maye with more facilitie and taſte godlily occupie them ſelues therein. Whiche I doubt not, my good brother, but thou ſhalte well proue, if thou be willing with
<pb facs="tcp:21583:8"/>
attention diligently to marke what ſhall in this little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe be layde before thée, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou ſhalt finde great ſwéete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in applying thy ſelfe to ſo heauenly an exerciſe, both ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and highly commended. For here thou ſhalte ſée in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures ſet foorth the Images of thoſe myſteries thou haſt to call to thy remembrance and mind: in beholding wherof thou maiſt be holpen to be more ſetled and ſtayed in memorie and minde of that imagination which is ſo imprinted within thée. Herein alſo are declared the poyntes to diſcourſe on, and ſo to procéede
<pb facs="tcp:21583:8"/>
with more deuotion in thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation. Or if thou knowe not howe of thy ſelfe to make theſe or the like talkes or ſpéeches with God, then I ſay, this may teache thée the order and maner howe, becauſe herein is ſhewed thée howe to geue thanks to thy Redéemer for that which thou ſhalt meditate or call to minde he hath ſuffred for thée: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo what thou oughteſt to praye for, conformable to that poynt and parte of the paſſion thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt to meditate vpon. Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oing (by Gods grace) with as great deuotion as thou canſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou mayſt then well hope thou
<pb facs="tcp:21583:9"/>
ſhalt not at any time be occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein without fruite: the which ſhal be ſo much the more, as thou ſhalt more earneſtlye perſeuer in ſo godly an exerciſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Diuers profitable wayes how to meditate vpon the bleſſed paſsion of Chriſt our Redeemer.</head>
               <p>IT is declared in the booke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Prophet Daniell, that there was ſhewed in a viſion to Nabuchodonoſor, a trée plante<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the middle of the earth, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> trée was very hye, garniſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with goodly leaues and abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dance
<pb facs="tcp:21583:9"/>
of fruite. By this trée is figured Chriſt crucified in the middeſt of the earth, vnder the ſhadow of which trée whoſoeuer is willing to reſt him ſelfe, and recorde within his minde the moſt holy paſſion, he ſhall finde fruite both ſwéete and copious, and that ſo muche the more, as his vnderſtanding ſhall ſerue him in more diuers ſort to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on the ſame. And therfore ye muſt note that ther be diuers wayes to meditate vpon the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſion, &amp; out of eche of them there may be gathered new va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of fruites: for that you ſhall finde one fruite and taſte
<pb facs="tcp:21583:10"/>
when you do in your meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take ſorow &amp; compaſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your ſelfe for the great tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; iniuries which Chriſt ſuffered: and an other kinde of fruite when thou ſhalt meditate thereon in minde to followe the great vertue that is taught thée therein, and ſo in diuers other ſortes, as your meditation may runne for diuers other endes and purpoſes. And although the deuotion of euery man may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe different wayes of exerciſe in this meditation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe I thought good in this litle treatiſe to ſet foorth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſortes, which I hope ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:21583:10"/>
not a little further and helpe ſuch as be willing to ſerue their turne therewith.</p>
               <p>The firſt maner or ſort which is generall, and here ſet foorth before the reſt we intende to ſpeake of, may be called hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall or literall: whiche conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in knowing wel the letter and hiſtorie of that myſterie which thou purpoſeſt to haue in minde and contemplation: the which thou muſt as freſhly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and conſider of, as it were preſently ſet before thine eyes.</p>
               <p>The ſecond maner of this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation is, by way of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:
<pb facs="tcp:21583:11"/>
that is to ſay, for that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that thou wouldeſt haue compaſſion, and as it were la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and be ſory for the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous tormentes, reproches and ſorowes which thou conceyueſt in thy minde that Chriſte hath ſuffred for thée: conſidering wel the quantitie and qualitie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with other circumſtances which do encreaſe the ſorowes and paſſion, and therefore the more ſtyrre thy heart to pitie and compaſſion.</p>
               <p>The third maner is, to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate by way of compunction or contrition, which is to that end that thou mayſt be pricked with
<pb facs="tcp:21583:11"/>
remorſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience and ſorow for thy ſinnes, which are with ſuch rigour and crueltie puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in thy redéemer, for that he was offered vp as a raunſome and price for them, ſo to make ſatiſfaction before the iuſtice of his eternall Father. And this ſhall cauſe thée to hate them the more, and to kéepe thy ſelfe the more warely hereafter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the like offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, when thou ſhalt conſider how muche they offended God, that he would puniſhe the ſame with ſo great ſeueritie.</p>
               <p>The fourth maner and ſort of meditation is, by way of imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:21583:12"/>
or following, that is, to the ende to followe the marueilous vertue and rare examples that Chriſte our redéemer ſhoweth and ſetteth foorth in his paſſion, as well in the wordes which he ſpake, as in the workes which he did, and in the maner of his ſuffering. All which to conſider is a certayne liuely example and paterne of perfection, for thée to vſe as a glaſſe to beholde what vertue wanteth in thée, and ſo to vſe thy ſelfe that thou mayeſt obtayne it.</p>
               <p>The fifth maner and ſorte of meditation is by way of thanks giuing, that is, in rendring of
<pb facs="tcp:21583:12"/>
thankes and prayſes to God for his bountifull goodneſſe, calling to remembraunce the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable giftes and great benefites which are giuen thée by meanes of this holy paſſion: the whiche are ſo great that no vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of man is able to compriſe them. Yet notwithſtanding, thoſe whiche by this diſcourſe thou art able to vnderſtande, may ſuffice to ſtirre thée to giue thankes and prayſe to thy Lord God, which hath done ſo muche for thée.</p>
               <p>The ſixt maner is by way of admiration: for hauing well conſidered in thy minde the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable
<pb facs="tcp:21583:13"/>
charitie and loue of Chriſte, in that he hath offered him ſelfe to ſuffer ſo bitter and ſhamefull death: and likewiſe the infinite wiſedome and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, declared in the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſion of his deare ſonne: thou ſhalt become as a man ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed out of him ſelfe, béeing amaſed of ſo high and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things.</p>
               <p>The ſeuenth maner is, by way of ioye and hope: For if thou conſider that all which Chriſte hath ſuffered, and that death which he hath ſuſtayned, was onely for thy remedie and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houe, and that by ſuch meanes
<pb facs="tcp:21583:13"/>
he would make ſatiſfaction for thy ſinnes, and leaue to thée the treaſures of his redemption and mercies, if thou be willing to helpe thy ſelfe therwith: Calling I ſay, theſe and the like thinges to thy remembraunce, they may cauſe thée to reioyce and be glad in hope that by this helpe thou mayſt agayne recouer that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite treaſure which thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt loſt, and he by this meanes hath purchaſed for thée.</p>
               <p>The eight and laſt maner of meditation vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this bleſſed paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is, by way of loue. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the principal fruite which thou mayſt ſéeme to gather of
<pb facs="tcp:21583:14"/>
that thou haſt meditate vpon, is a certayne excéeding tender loue of our Lorde him ſelfe, which ſo vouchſafed to ſuffer and dye for thée.</p>
               <p>And nowe that thou mayſt in all theſe maners and wayes of meditation knowe the better how to procéede, theſe inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and declarations following may ſerue thy turne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Declarations of the ſayde ſortes and maners of meditations vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the bleſſed paſsion, and firſt concerning the firſt kind, called hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or litterall.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:14"/>THE firſt manner howe to be occupied in meditation vpon the moſt bleſſed paſſion of our redéemer, we haue ſayde it may be termed hiſtoricall or literall, becauſe in it we preſuppoſe chiefly that the hiſtory of things whiche happened and came to paſſe, are therein contayned. Vpon the which foundation all the other ſortes of meditation are grounded, which we haue before ſpecified. And therefore it is neceſſarie that this kinde and ſort go before the other: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, this remembraunce what things Chriſt ſuffered, is of it ſelfe laudable inough, and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:15"/>
commended in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: as it appeareth in that which the Prophet Ieremie in perſon of our Lorde ſayde: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thou my pouertie, my wormwood and gall. And in an other place our Lorde him ſelfe doth likewiſe lament vs that we haue likewiſe forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, and that which he hath done and ſuffered for vs. That we maye therefore the better exerciſe our ſelfe in this kind of meditation, it behoueth often to reade the hiſtorie of the paſſion as the foure Euangeliſtes do ſet foorth the ſame, and is to be founde in certayne godly bookes, or els to
<pb facs="tcp:21583:15"/>
be learned at ſermons, or by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpiritual talke, ſo that thou muſt trauell to haue the ſame well fixed and rooted in thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, imagining and thinking alwayes vpon it, chewing it in thy minde, vntill thou finde thy ſelfe ſo ready and prompt in it, that if thou were appoſed in any part of the hiſtorie of the paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou mighteſt be able to anſwer to it, &amp; declare it perfectly. And to this it ſhal helpe thée often to exerciſe thy ſelfe in meditation of Chriſtes paſſion. Alſo to this maner it doth apperteine to cal to thy remembraunce according to that which thou haſt read or
<pb facs="tcp:21583:16"/>
learned by bookes or preaching, that whatſoeuer thou ſeeſt in thy contemplation thy ſauiour to haue ſuffred, they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore figured and foreſhowen by many holy Prophetes. And ſo thou ſhalt knowe and well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that the truth of that thou goeſt about to meditate, doth anſwere to the olde figures and auncient prophecies: the which ſhall miniſter gret cauſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and more confirme thée in faith, and alſo chaſe and driue away all other fancies whiche diſtract the minde, and make the ſame more attentiue and ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the matter in meditation.
<pb facs="tcp:21583:16"/>
And ſo this ſhall be as a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to paſſe further to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſiderations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ A declaration of the ſeconde manner of meditation, which is by way of compaſsion.</head>
               <p>The ſeconde maner of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation vpon the bleſſed paſſion, which is by way of compaſſion, is more acceptable to our Lord, and that is to endeuour to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell in ſorrow and griefe with him. And it is alſo no leſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for vs, for that, as Saint Paule ſayth, if we will ſuffer with Chriſt, we ſhal alſo reigne
<pb facs="tcp:21583:17"/>
together with Chriſt. In this kinde the matter of meditation is ſo plentiful and copious, that it ſhuld be long to write or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate the ſame at large: and therfore it ſhall ſuffice to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therein two poyntes, to the which the other may be reduced that are vſed for that purpoſe to be conſidered of. The firſt is, to conſider the perſon that ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth. The ſeconde, to conſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the thing which he ſuffereth: th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which two poyntes well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of, may ſuffice to moue a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny hard hart to compaſſion. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what hart will not mollifie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> melt to conſider, firſt the quali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:21583:17"/>
which do concurre in the perſon that would ſuffer béeing very God &amp; man? And touching his diuine nature, no man is able to declare or comprehende neither his generation, nor his dignitie, nor his maieſtie, nor his highneſſe, nor his eternitie, nor yet the fulnes of his perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And touching his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, he is moſt noble of blood royal, the ſonne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt cleare Virgin mother, formed by the operation of the holy Ghoſt, the moſt beautifull body that euer was ſéene amongſt men, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt gracious, ſwete, humble, meeke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouing, with all other excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb facs="tcp:21583:18"/>
more then can be thought. And touching the ſoule, in him is the fulneſſe of grace, of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, of holynes, of all other noble vertues and heauenly giftes, in more high degrée then euer was communicate to any creature. And this ſuch and ſo mightie a Lord did ſuffer, béeing moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent without any faulte or ſinne, more grieuous payns and terrible tormentes then mans tongue or Angels can expreſſe.</p>
               <p>Nowe let this be the ſeconde poynt, that is to ſay, the things which he hath ſuffred: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thou haſt to remember in thy meditation, howe he ſuffered in
<pb facs="tcp:21583:18"/>
his body from the crowne of his head to the ſole of his foote, from top to toe, yea, and in al his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and féelings, and ſo running in through diſcourſe of them, thou ſhalt finde that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned in him no one part nor ſence, or féeling, in the which he did not ſuffer ſo many ſortes of tormentes as can not be thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght, yea and that in fleſhe moſte tender, delicate, and quicke to féele for the perfection of his complexion. Conſider here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that he dyed in the flowre of his age, when to liue was moſt ſwéete, and death the cauſe of more ſorrowe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:19"/>Remember alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blaſphemies they gaue him, the iniuries, the reproches, the ſcornings &amp; moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings they deuiſed againſt him, ſometimes clothing him in one faſhion of garment, &amp; ſomtimes in an other, with ſo many kinds of mockinges: and finallye in ſpoyling and ſtripping him bare and crucifying him naked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuche a multitude of people that it can not be declared, and it paſſeth mans wit to expreſſe howe great the ſpite and ſhame was they wrought againſt him. O infinite heape of ſorrowes and reproches ſo great, that there can not be found the wit
<pb facs="tcp:21583:19"/>
or vnderſtanding to thinke, nor yet tong finde words to expreſſe and vtter them: yea or howe much ſoeuer they were able to thinke or vtter, yet ſhould it be the leaſt part of all that he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. O my Redéemer how well worthy maye thoſe wordes be ſpoken of thée by the Prophet Ieremie: O all ye that paſſe by the way conſider and ſée, if there were euer any ſorow like vnto mine. And ſo truly it is, O our Lorde, that like as there was neuer loue to be compared to thine: ſo alſo verily there was neuer ſorrowe like nor equall vnto thine, neither in quantitie
<pb facs="tcp:21583:20"/>
nor in qualitie, nor yet in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtances that can be imagined. How then, good bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, can thy hart holde out and not with pitie relent and melt, and with compaſſion be moued, when thou ſhalt conſider theſe and many other things whiche thou mayeſt call to thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and which do aggrauate and make more lamentable the bitterneſſe, the ſorrowes, the tormentes and great iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done to thy Sauiour? And this is that he ſuffered in his body and to our ſight outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which in déede was the leaſt part, becauſe muche more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous
<pb facs="tcp:21583:20"/>
and percing were the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſorowes, paynes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of his moſte bleſſed ſoule. As that his ſorrowe vnto death did witneſſe which he ſaid he felte, and alſo that agonie which he ſuffered in his prayer, hauing diuers and infinite ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of paynes before his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſight: whiche ſo troubled and tormented him, that it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to ſweate that bloody ſweate, trickling downe from his face and body to the ground. The cauſes of that ſo greate heauineſſe and affliction of his bleſſed ſoule, may in our medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation be gathered to be theſe:
<pb facs="tcp:21583:21"/>
Firſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration he had of the ſinnes of all people from the beginning of the world in time paſt, time preſent, and time to come: the number, the malice, and wickednes, the abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he both ſaw, and euidently knewe, and playnly vnderſtood, how great iniurie and diſhonor they committed thereby againſt his eternall father, whom he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other things loued, and deſired to honour, the which did gréeue and torment him more then all thoſe outward torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Secondly he ſorrowed for the vnkindnes and vnthankfulnes of men, and chiefly Chriſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:21"/>
for whom he gaue his life and offred him ſelfe to ſo great and bitter payne, and yet he ſawe they would not endeuour nor begin to know, nor eſtéeme or care to helpe them ſelfe with ſo great and ineſtimable benefite: and ſo through their owne fault he ſhould not gayne by his grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous paſſion &amp; death that fruite for the whiche he traueled ſo ſore, and which he might haue had, if they them ſelues would haue diſpoſed their good willes thereto, which did more grieue him then death it ſelfe. And that he playnly ſhoweth where he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth by the mouth of the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:22"/>
Prophet Eſay, ſaying, in vayne haue I traueled, and without cauſe and fruite haue I conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med my ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Thirdly he ſorowed much the damnation of Iudas, and of ſo great a multitude of people o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, whome he knewe ſhoulde be damned for deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of that moſte holſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine he ſhould leaue for them in his precious blood: and that by howe muche the more with infinite charitie he deſired their health and ſaluation, ſo muche the more it grieued him to ſée their perdition, and alſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the ineſtimable ryches
<pb facs="tcp:21583:22"/>
they loſte, and the horrible tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes wherein they ſhould for euer be puniſhed. This was a cauſe of more bitter ſorrowe to him, then the cup of his paſſion.</p>
               <p>Fourthly the repreſentation of that ſword of ſorowes which he knewe ſhould paſſe through the virgin hart of his moſt dere mother, was likewiſe a cauſe of great griefe and ſadnes. For he knew ſhe would accompanie him in the middle of his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and the ſight of her did encreaſe the ſame through the tender compaſſion he had of her. And likewiſe he did ſorowe and pitie the ſolitarines, cares, and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:23"/>
trauels his diſciples ſhould be left in, and all his friends both preſent, and all other his elect that ſhould come vnto the ende of the world, of whoſe perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, torments &amp; tribulations he did no leſſe grieue at &amp; féele, then the head doth féele payne &amp; griefe when any of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers doth ſuffer. Sée then how diuers ſorts of ſorowes, beſides many other, a man may call to remembraunce and meditate, that perced and ranne through his moſt ſacred ſoule, and thoſe he felt, euery payne by it ſelfe, the one not letting the griefe of the other, and that without all
<pb facs="tcp:21583:23"/>
conſolation or comfort, without eaſe or reſt, and béeing forſaken of all parts, as he declared vpon the croſſe, when he ſayd: O God my god why haſt thou forſaken me? And as it is ſayd of him in an other place, That he was made as a man without helpe. For ſo it pleaſed his entier loue the more to ſuffer for vs, and ſo to make the greater ſatiſfaction to the iuſtice of God. O loue without meaſure, O infinite clemencie and pitie moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently declared, in that thou wouldeſt ſhowe thy ſelfe cruell to thy ſelf, to be pitiful towards vs: And that thou more eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medſt
<pb facs="tcp:21583:24"/>
our health, then thy owne comfort and life. Séeing that béeing depriued of all comforte and helpe, thou waſt drowned in a bottomleſſe pit of ſo great griefes and ſorowes, and waſt content to be ſwallowed vp as an other Ionas in the belly of the whale of death. What man then can finde in his heart to be ſo voyde of all pitie, that thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon theſe thinges, will not be mollified and moued to compaſſion? Séeing he woulde be ſorie (I trowe) for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemie he had, if he ſhould ſée him in like torment of body and ſoule without all eaſe and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:24"/>
comfort?</p>
               <p>Lo then, my dere brother, how in theſe poyntes hitherto is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared what was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon that ſuffered, and what he ſuffred as well in body as in ſoule: wherin thou ſhalt finde ſufficient mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſtyrre thée to compaſſion, which is the ende we purpoſed in this part. For if thou medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate and conſider in thy minde after this ſorte this holy myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, it can not be but if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member well the aforeſayde things with good attention and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euotion, it ſhall moue &amp; breake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy hart were it neuer ſo hard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing that the very ſtones in the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:25"/>
ſtréete brake and ſhiuered in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſame thy Sauiour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A declaration of the third man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meditation, by way of contrition and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction.</head>
               <p>The third maner we purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to teache thée howe to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the bleſſed paſſion, is by the way of contrition and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction: the ende wherof is, to haue an inward ſorowe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of thy ſinnes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the maieſtie of God: and to find out the fruit of this, which is not a litle, it behoueth
<pb facs="tcp:21583:25"/>
a man to ground him ſelfe vpon this veritie, that all which chriſt our redéemer hath ſuffred, was for the ſinnes of the world. In ſo much that if man had not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Chriſt had not ſuffred nor dyed, for ſo the diuine ſcripture affirmeth, that for the ſinnes of the people he was ſtroken of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ternal father, and that he layde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon his ſhoulders the ſinnes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s al, and that he was ſcourged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd wounded for our iniquitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd beaten and buffeted for our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſeruing. And this veritie is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onfirmed by many other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>horities, aſwell of the olde as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he new Teſtament. Now then
<pb facs="tcp:21583:26"/>
this ſo béeing, when thou ſhalt be diſpoſed to make diſcourſe and occupie thy minde in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the death and paſſion of thy Redéemer, thou haſte to think verily, that thou waſt the cauſe of all thoſe ſorrowes, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and iniuries, whiche thou ſeeſt him to haue ſuffered. For notwithſtanding he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and dyed for all, yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe he dyed as well for thée alone, as he dyed for all. So that thou mayeſt truely ſaye with Saint Paule, that he was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred for thée, that he was ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for thée, that he was nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on the Croſſe for thée, and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:26"/>
dyed for thée. And likewiſe that thy ſinnes killed him, thy pride crowned him with thorne, thy diſhoneſties &amp; filthy life ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him, thy drunkenneſſe and gluttony gaue him the eyſel and gall, thy diſorderlye doinges and ſinnes were the cauſes of his grieuous ſorowes, and that thy ſins were thoſe many dogs and great bulles, of whom he ſaid he was enuironed or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed round about: and ſo when thou ſhalt beholde him in the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>full image where Pilate ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth him to the Iewes when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayde, Beholde the man: then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſo remember that our Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:21583:27"/>
ſayth the very ſame wordes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée: Behold, O man, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde I haue receiued for thée, Behold howe I am handled for thée, Beholde howe I ſuffer the ſcourge of thy deſeruings, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what thy vnthankfulneſſe hath cauſed me to haue, Behold the deformed picture and image which thy ſinnes haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, in recompence of my good wil to make thée partaker of my beau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie. Of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration we ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoone conceiue in our mind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what an horrible thing ſinne is which in ſuch ſort hath handle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſonne of God, and how ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hominable the filth thereof is
<pb facs="tcp:21583:27"/>
which hath outwardly ſo beray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, darkned, ſtayned and ſoyled him, which is the very myrror and glaſſe without ſpotte, the brightnes of eternall life. This wel conſidered and called to thy remembraunce, ſhall ſtrike into thy hart gret hatred and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of thy ſinnes, which were the cauſe of ſo ſore paynes and puniſhmentes of thy Redéemer which neuer committed ſinne, neither anye guyle was euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in his mouth. And ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he more thou oughteſt to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow and lament thy ſinnes, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow much the oftener thou haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>allen into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For euery time
<pb facs="tcp:21583:28"/>
thou haſt ſinned as the Apoſtle ſaith, ſo often thou haſt gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to crucifie and deſpiſe the ſonne of God. And if they for their parte ſhould repent them ſelues and be grieuouſly ſorye, which once onely offended him mortally and crucified him: how much more oughteſt thou to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and be ſory, whiche haſte crucified him ſo many times. This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce maye ſtrike into thée ſometimes ſuche ſorowe and feare of thy ſelfe, that it ſhall prouoke thée to ſay theſe or the like wordes: Ah my God and gracious Lorde, where was my
<pb facs="tcp:21583:28"/>
iudgement &amp; wit, when I was ſo bolde to commit ſuche ſinnes againſt thy diuine maieſtie? where was my vnderſtanding that could not remember howe that eury time I ſinned I went about to crucifie thée againe? how is it poſſible that I ſhould imploy my hands to offend thée, thou hauing thy hands nayled on the croſſe to ſaue me? howe could I open my mouth to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme thée, thou hauing opened thy mouth ſo often to pray for me? howe is my harte become ſo harde and ſtubborne to loue thée and obay thée, ſéeing thine hart with a ſpere euen through
<pb facs="tcp:21583:29"/>
perced, to ſhewe the great loue thou bareſt me? Thou ſhalt not onely learne by this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how to hate and be ſory for thy ſinnes paſſed, but alſo it ſhal moue thée with more earneſt purpoſe euer after to flye ſuche ſinnes, fearing agayne to runne vnto the horrible abhomination to go about to crucifie Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, and likewiſe cauſe thée to be afrayed of the great pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which thou ſhouldeſt deſerue, if with newe ſins thou go about to defile thy ſelf again. If the ſonne of a Prince would be afrayed when for the fault that he him ſelfe committeth, he
<pb facs="tcp:21583:29"/>
doth ſée his page or ſlaue beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: how much more ought the ſlaue to feare, when he ſéeth the ſonne of the Prince beaten for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fault which he the ſlaue him ſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth? Feare thou then and tremble, miſerable wretch, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for thy fault the ſonne of God thy king and Lorde is bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſo cruelly handled, and call to thy remembraunce the words he ſpake to the women that wept when they ſawe him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare the croſſe: If they do this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the gréene trée, what ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one in the dry wood? That is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſay, If in Chriſt which is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>réene trée, full of the leaues of
<pb facs="tcp:21583:30"/>
moſt holy words and fruites of moſt excellent works, ſo ſeuere puniſhment is vſed, for that he hath taken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him our ſinnes: what ſhal be done to thée which art a dry withered trée yéelding no good fruites, neither of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience nor of charitie, nor of any vertue, nor yet is there to be ſéene in thée ſo much as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaues of words profitable to thy ſelfe or any other, and much leſſe any one flowre of liuely deſire to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende thyne owne life? If thou then ſhalte be a trée not onely barren and fruitleſſe, but alſo vitious and laden with moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and wicked fruites: wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:30"/>
ſhall become of thée, but that which is vſed to be done of the like trée, that is, to be cut down and caſt into the fyre? And that ſhalt thou haue worſe then any other trée, for that the fyre of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wood is ſoone conſumed, but thy fyre ſhall be euerlaſting. Sée therfore how this meditation of Chriſtes holy paſſion ſhal cauſe thée to ſorrow for thy ſinne paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; to feare the ſins to come, becauſe thou wouldeſt not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly fall into the iuſtice of god the which thou ſéeſt ſo rigorou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly and ſharply executed vpon thy ſauiour, in that he was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to pay thy raunſome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21583:31"/>
               <head>The fourth maner of meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is by way of imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or following.</head>
               <p>The fourth maner howe to meditate and conſider vpon the bleſſed paſſion, we ſayde it was by the way of imitation, which is of muche fruite, and highly commended by holy men. For as the chiefe of the Apoſtles S. Peter ſaith, one cauſe why that Chriſt ſuffered for vs, was, to leaue vs an example to followe his ſteps. And Chriſt him ſelfe ſayth, that he hath giuen vs an example to do as he hath done. Which ſo being, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalt occupie thy ſelfe in meditating
<pb facs="tcp:21583:31"/>
vpon his paſſion, marke wel the manyfold and marueilous ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues which he teacheth therein, as well in that he ſuffered, as in the maner of his ſuffering: the which thou muſt deſire to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low by his grace as much as is poſſible in thée, ſtaying thy ſelfe chiefly vpon the conſideration of that vertue which thou kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt principally to be lacking in thée. And becauſe it may ſeme impoſſible to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider all the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues whiche ſhine in his moſte glorious paſſion, who was the moſt perfect paterne of all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and perfection, I will onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et here before thy eyes thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:21583:32"/>
which thou oughteſt moſt often to remember, and whiche be moſte neceſſarie for thy turne. And firſt to beginne with thoſe two vertues whiche our Lorde ſpecially commendeth vnto vs by his owne example, and to be learned of him, ſaying, Learne ye of me, becauſe I am méeke and humble of heart: Conſider (I ſay) howe perfectly he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth them in his bleſſed paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Humilitie which is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all vertues, he declareth playnely in humbling him ſelfe to ſo ſhamefull a death, as that of the croſſe, diſdaining not that the very thief Barrabas found
<pb facs="tcp:21583:32"/>
more friendſhip and fauour to be deliuered before him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing content to be crucified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene two théeues.</p>
               <p>In many other things thou mayſt by diſcourſe call to mind &amp; conſider that louely humilitie which he ſetteth forth in the reſt of his life, aſwel as in his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that in waſhing the féete of Iudas &amp; of his other diſciples not long before, &amp; in being born in an oxe ſtall or ſtable, with many other examples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vertue, whereof both the reſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s life &amp; death are full. For in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s birth, in his liuing, &amp; in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, he neuer ceaſſed to leaue
<pb facs="tcp:21583:33"/>
vs all examples that might be of ſo neceſſarie a vertue for vs. He ſhewed alſo a marueilous example of méekenes in his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly paſſion, when he was led vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to death (as the Prophet Eſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpake of him) euen as ſhepe, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtoode as gentle as a lambe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore them who ſo cruelly han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led him, not once opening hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mouth to ſpeake an euill word againſt them which railed vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, nor yet to threaten the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which tormented him. In lyk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maner he declared his modeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſoberneſſe in that clere an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lightſome countenance of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtanding before the Iudges an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:33"/>
his accuſers, and in the maner of his anſwering to their que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and in that peaceable calmneſſe of minde whcih he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes expreſſed, not once being troubled in his countenance or chaunging moode, although he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere neuer ſo muche iniuried, and wrongfully ſlaundered. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eclared alſo his perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not onely béeing obedient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o his eternall Father, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommandement of death which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e gaue him, but alſo declared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſame in euery thing, euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owardes his wicked enemies whiche crucified him, in dooing whatſoeuer they willed: as in
<pb facs="tcp:21583:34"/>
ſuffering him ſelfe to be ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of his clothes, and agayne to be clothed, and that as often as pleaſed them to commaunde him: Nowe going to one iudge, and now vnto an other, as they woulde haue him: and finally when he was appoynted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, he bare the Croſſe whereon he ſhould be crucified. What ſhal we then ſay of the ſoftneſſe, and of the ſilence he obſerued and kept in all that pitifull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant of his paſſion? He was not deſirous to multiply words nor to anſwere ſo many iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and blaſphemies they ſpake agaynſt him, neither to defende
<pb facs="tcp:21583:34"/>
him ſelfe agaynſt the falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe they brought foorth, ne to excuſe him ſelfe of that they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly accuſed him and layde to his charge: But he ſuffered pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently all things, without aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering of any thing, euen as though he had bene domme. So that he therin well fulfilled that whiche was written of him: I as a deafe man did not heare, and as a domme creature which openeth not his mouth, I made no aunſwere. And the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt affirmeth, that euen the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry iudge Pilate him ſelfe dyd much maruel at his gret ſilence. But much more his inuincible
<pb facs="tcp:21583:35"/>
patience may cauſe vs to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, with the which he ſuffered and bare, not only the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſcornes, ſkoffes, and moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, with other outrages de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed agaynſt him, but alſo the gréeuous ſorowes and paynes, the moſt bitter tormentes they coulde inuent to puniſhe him withall, whiche were ſo many and ſo cruell, that they might ſuffice to breake any hard ſtone. Verifying in this that whiche Ezechiel propheſied of him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he likened his face to the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond and hard flint, becauſe of the hardnes wherewith he bare ſo many blowes and buffettes,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:35"/>
with their fiſts and hard gaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets: and all with ſuche an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible patience, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king reſiſtance at all, ne yet ſo muche as any ſhow of murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or grudging. And likewiſe conſider howe that his moſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent and burning charitie was not able to be quenched or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed with all the waters of thoſe his afflictions and ſorows which entred into him, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced euen through the very mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of his moſt bleſſed ſoule: but rather the more they doubled his torments, the more increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flame of loue, by the which in his moſt exceſſiue ſorows he
<pb facs="tcp:21583:36"/>
prayed for them that crucified him, and excuſed them before his father who accuſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned him. Furthermore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that intier deare mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his, that where he ſaw our great miſeries and calamities, he had compaſſion vpon vs, and wéeped for our ſakes, he prayed for vs, and ſhedde his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood, thereby to heale and cure our gréeuous diſeaſes and daungerous woundes. Call al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to minde and conſider that fortitude and magnanimitie of his, who knowing (as noteth the Euangeliſt Saint Iohn) all things that ſhould be done vnto
<pb facs="tcp:21583:36"/>
him, that is to ſaye, the great battayle which was prepared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt him, and in the whiche he ſhoulde dye with ſo many gréeuous tormentes and deadly woundes: yet feared he nothing at all to marche forwarde to méete his enemies in the face, and offer him ſelfe into their hands, to execute what crueltie they would vpon him.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo his conſtante perſeuerance, which is a vertue that crowneth and rewardeth all our good workes: Becauſe who ſo euer ſhall perſeuer and continue in well dooing to the ende, he ſhall be ſaued. Which
<pb facs="tcp:21583:37"/>
vertue is in none better ſéene then in Chriſt, who in ſuch ſorte perſeuered, continued, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tly went forward with that wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of our redemption he had bego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that neither the feare of paine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, nor ſtrokes, nor iniuries, nor ſcornes, nor threatnings, foule wordes nor fayre promiſes, nor men, nor diuels, could be able to make him come down from the Croſſe, or leaue vndone any one iote of that was to be done, for finiſhing of the worke of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption which his Father had commaunded him.</p>
               <p>Nor yet leaue thou here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remembred both for thy conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb facs="tcp:21583:37"/>
and example to folow his bleſſed ſtepps, that contempt of the world, and that his extreme pouertie, whereof he giueth vs notable examples both in his bleſſed paſſion &amp; death, and alſo in his life and conuerſation, which was full of pouertie and contempt of honour and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fauour. But ſpecially it is to be ſéene in his paſſion and ende of his life, becauſe he dyed in that ſtraite bedde of the Croſſe, hauing nothing at all to leane his head vpon, ſtanding ſpoyled and naked with ſo great ſhame and ignominie in that multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people beholding and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:38"/>
gaſing vppon him. And in the thirſt and drineſſe which he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred, they gaue him not ſo much as a cup of water, but only bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gal and vineger. There was not one that mighte helpe or comfort him with any eaſe or reliefe: but rather thoſe his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies ſtudied by all deuiſes and inuentions they could, new kindes of paynes and wayes, how to vexe and diſgrace him.</p>
               <p>O my God, what is that man, but if he will remember this, and marke it well, may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to murmure, grudge, and lament him ſelfe of any griefe or aduerſity that he doth ſuffer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:38"/>
What pouerty or barenneſſe in the worlde may be compared to thine? what abſtinence, what auſteritie of life, or ſtraitneſſe of penance was euer ſo harde and ſharpe, which may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to that thou diddeſt ſuffer on the Croſſe? what man was euer in the world ſo deſpiſed, ſo mocked, and ſo perſecuted, as thou waſte in thy paſſion and death? Truely, O Lorde, he that can well remember and conſider thée, maye ſhutte his mouth &amp; ſhame to lament him ſelf at al, either of pouerty, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, thirſt, nakedneſſe, vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or of any other lacke or
<pb facs="tcp:21583:39"/>
griefe that he ſuffereth. He may be aſhamed to ſée howe fayntly and coldly he traueleth to folow thée, O Lord, being ſet before vs as an example and rule of our life. Thou ſeeſt now good bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what order thou muſte ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, béeing after this ſort oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in thy meditation vpon the paſſion. Beholde the pure and cleare glaſſe in the whiche thou mayſt looke and learne to knowe and ſée in thy ſelfe thy faults, deformities and defects, and then compare them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his vertues and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: becauſe thou ſhalte ſo vnderſtand how great thy pride
<pb facs="tcp:21583:39"/>
is, if thou beholde and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his lowlyneſſe, méeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and humilitie: how great is thy coldneſſe, in compariſon to his tender and burning cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: and the like of other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues aforeſaid, and many more that may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered of, which ſhal diſcouer and open vnto thée thy lackes and imperfections, thy fouleneſſe and deformities. And ſo ſhalt thou be encouraged with more diligence to beſtirre thée, to worke according to this examplar and paterne ſhowed vnto thée in this mount of moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh perfection, as it was ſayde vnto Moyſes: Becauſe in this
<pb facs="tcp:21583:40"/>
imitation &amp; conforming of thy life after the example of Chriſt, conſiſteth the greateſt merite thou canſt haue in this life, and the greateſt rewarde prepared for thée in the life to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A declaration of the fyfth man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meditation, which is in thankeſgeuing.</head>
               <p>The fifth manner of medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon the holy paſſion, is by way of thankeſgiuing, whiche we are bounde often to do. For if we ought of very duetie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we woulde not fall into the vice of ingratitude, whiche ſo muche diſpleaſeth God, and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:40"/>
no leſſe hurteth vs, to call of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en times to our remembrance ſuche other benefites as we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue receyued at Gods hande, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to thanke his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and liberalitie for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame: How muche more ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſo to do for the benefite of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur redemption, the whiche ſo much more paſſeth all other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efites, as it hath by our redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er with more deare coſte and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rice, and for our greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite, bene purchaſed?</p>
               <p>A great matter it was that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e gaue vs a ſoule and body, with all our members and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, and muche it is to be eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:41"/>
that for our conſeruation and benefite he hath created the heauens and the earth, with ſo many and diuers creatures as we ſée in it. But what ſhould it haue profited vs to be borne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, if we had not bene redéemed? Of what eſtimation or valour might our creation haue bene thought, if our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption had lacked? For by the firſt we receiued but our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by this ſeconde we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued our wel béeing. The firſt thing coſt our creator but litle, for that he created vs and al the world with his onely word, and in a ſhort time: but as for the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:41"/>
ſeconde, who is able to declare how dearly and with how great expence our redéemer purchaſed and bought it? Séeing that with the trauels and ſweat of thrée and thirtie yeres, &amp; finally with tormentes and death vpon the Croſſe he gaue vs life, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired the worlde which in ſixe dayes he had made.</p>
               <p>Nowe if it ſéeme to thée that thou art litle bound to him for that whiche coſt him litle, yet thou canſt not denie but that thou art muche in his debt, and very greatly bounde vnto him, for that thing he payed ſo dearly for. Thou ſhalt do then right, as
<pb facs="tcp:21583:42"/>
the wiſe man giueth thée coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, not to forget the grace and benefites thou haſte receiued of ſuch a benefactour, that hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his life for thée. Conſider if thou haddeſt receyued of anye man the like benefite, how gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhouldeſt thou haue remained bounde: howe highly wouldeſt thou haue prayſed him? howe wouldeſt thou haue endeuoured thy ſelfe to haue ſerued him? And therefore thou mayſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade with thy ſelfe how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou art bounde to God thy Creator and Redéemer: for if thou mighteſt poſſibly be bound to any other man whiche had
<pb facs="tcp:21583:42"/>
deliuered thée from a corporall death: howe muche more ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou to be bounde to him that hath deliuered thée from the ſpirituall death of the ſoule? And if thou wouldeſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thy ſelfe muche beholden to a man that had ſuffered a little for thée: then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber howe muche more thou oweſt to him that is both God and man, who hath ſuffered ſuche paynes and tormentes for thée, and not onely tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, but alſo moſte bitter and ſhamefull death, through which thy ſinnes were cancelled and raſed oute of remembraunce,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:43"/>
the might of the diuell was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to péeces, peace and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation was made with God, the gates of heauen opened, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other innumerable giftes giuen thée. And ſéeing thou canſt not better recompence this ſo great debte, then to knowe, to loue, and to be thankfull to thy benefactour: why then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to offer to him the often ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of prayſe and thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, as the holy king &amp; prophet Dauid exhorteth and encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth thée to do, ſtyrring vp thy ſoule with thoſe words where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he lifted vp his owne hart and ſoule vnto God, ſaying: O
<pb facs="tcp:21583:43"/>
my ſoule bleſſe the Lord, and all the powers within me prayſe ye his holy name. O my ſoule bleſſe thy Lorde, and forget not how great benefites he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon thée. But yet chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly remember the greateſt of all the reſt, which is, to haue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered thy life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternal death, and to crowne thée with mercy in his glory, if the fault be not in thy ſelfe. As verily it ſhal not be, whenſoeuer thou ſhalt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare thy ſelfe thankfull for his giftes receiued: And that ſhalte thou do in exerciſing thy ſelfe to giue prayſe and thankes to the giuer therof. And think it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:21583:44"/>
thy duetie, as often as in this maner thou art diſpoſed to meditate vpon the bleſſed paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to remember and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour by all meanes, earneſtly to giue thanks and prayſe for that entier louing charitie of thy Sauiour, that woulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déeme thée with his owne blood, and for that incomparable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of his, by the which he ſuffered all thoſe ſorrowes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, mockes, and ſcornes, as thou ſhalt call to thy minde, béeing after this ſorte occupied in thy meditation. And albeit that the giuing of thanks which in this litle treatiſe is ſet in the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:44"/>
ende of euery prayer, may helpe and ſerue thée to that effect: yet neuertheleſſe it ſhal further thée muche, that in thy diſcourſe of meditation thou deuiſe of thy ſelfe newe prayſes and thankes giuing, ſayinge ſometimes: Thanks be to thée, O my God, for thy excéeding charitie. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mayeſt thou be in thy pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that wouldeſt ſuffer ſuche tormentes for me. O moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Lamb, prayſed and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be thy méekeneſſe. Let thy Angels in my behalf bleſſe thée, that wouldeſt ſo muche humble thy ſelfe. And at an other time ſaye: When ſhall I be able,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:45"/>
O my Lord, to recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce theſe and other ſo great paynes and ſorowes, ſhames and reproches which thou haſt ſuffred for me? Let euery ſpirite and creature confeſſe thy mercies, and be thankfull therefore.</p>
               <p>And ſo vſing ſuche other lyke words of prayſes, according as thy deuotion ſhall moue thée.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A declaration of the ſixt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meditation, which is by way of admiration.</head>
               <p>The ſixt maner is, according to our former diuiſion in order, of admiration: which thy ſoule ſhall féele to be very great, if
<pb facs="tcp:21583:45"/>
thou knowe once howe to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thy ſelfe well in that ſort of conſideration. And ſéeing that the Prophet Dauid vſed, as he affirmeth of him ſelfe, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and meditate in his minde the maruellous works of God, ſo is it good reaſon that thou do exerciſe thy ſelfe in the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his moſt holy paſſion and death, which is the moſte mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous worke amongſt all that he hath wrought. And who will not maruell when he conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that ſuche a one did ſuffer, who is the only refuge and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of al thoſe that do ſuffer? And that he is ſadde and heauy
<pb facs="tcp:21583:46"/>
for ſorowe, who is the mirth and comforte of Angels: And that he is deſpiſed and ſcorned, who is that Lorde before whoſe ſighte the powers of heauen feare and tremble? Who can but wonder when he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth that he dyed, who is the lyfe of all thinges liuing? O howe aptly to this did the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Abacuc, vnderſtanding in the ſpirite of propheſie, ſay: Lorde I conſidered thy works, and I was afrayde. And true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the cauſes of wonder be ſo greate to make a man muſe thereat, that it is more maruell to ſée one not maruel and muſe,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:46"/>
then one that dothe muſe and maruell at it. For howe can it be, deare brother, but thou muſt maruell and wonder, if thou conſider the greatnes, the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, the highneſſe, and the eternall maieſtie of him that ſuffered ſo many kindes of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, of iniuries, of tormentes, and of ſo ſhamefull a death? And contrariwiſe, the baſenes, the vileneſſe, and the vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of men, for whom he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. And if any of theſe things being by itſelfe conſidered, haue cauſe ſufficient to make thée maruell: what ſhal it be if thou ioyne all together that his high
<pb facs="tcp:21583:47"/>
maieſtie hath ſuffred ſuche and ſo great tormentes for ſo baſe and vile creatures? That is to ſay, that the iudge of the liuing and the dead was crucified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene two théeues: that the king of glory which is adored of Angels, was blaſphemed of moſt vile men: who woulde not maruell? who would not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayd? who would not be aſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to thinke vpon it?</p>
               <p>This is one thing that ſhall giue thée copious matter to wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and maruell: to conſider the infinite loue, bountie, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, in this worke of thy redemption declared. And thou
<pb facs="tcp:21583:47"/>
ſhalt no leſſe maruell, if thou conſider the great wiſedome he ſheweth in the ſame his paſſion and croſſe: in that he found out ſo conuenient and apt meane to vanquiſh and ouercome our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, euen as it were with the ſame weapon wherwith he ouercame vs. And this is it that the Catholike Churche ſingeth: That he ordeined the trée of the croſſe to be the inſtrument and meane of our ſaluation: becauſe the diuell, like as he wanne the victorie ouer vs by one trée: ſo likewiſe he might be vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and troden vnder foote by an other trée. Alſo his croſſe and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:48"/>
paſſion was a moſt preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie for all our infirmities. For he humbling himſelfe euen to the death of the croſſe, did pay ſufficiently the price of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and pride: Geuing vs the greateſt example that might be of his humilitie, which is ſo neceſſarie a vertue for vs, beſides diuerſe examples els, as of deſpiſing the worlde, and of many other vertues ſpoken of before. By meanes whereof we maye knowe our owne vices and amende them, and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly renounce and forſake our ſelfe-loue, which is the roote of all vice.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:48"/>Alſo the remembraunce of his Croſſe and paſſion may encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs to ſuffer and patiently beare the manyfolde trauels, miſeries, and griefes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of our life is full: For what greater comforte can there be had then to beholde Chriſt nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on the Croſſe? whoſe woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are ſufficient to heale our woundes: whoſe paynes and griefe if we well conſider them, may cauſe vs not ſo impatient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to take our troubles what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they be. And likewiſe to inflame and kindle our loue towardes him, there can not be founde a better meane
<pb facs="tcp:21583:49"/>
then to lay before our eyes how gretly and entierly he loued vs, in ſuffering ſo much for vs, and that he hath left vs ſo great ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his mercies, of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of examples, of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts, of ſatiſfactions, of fayth, of hope, of deuotion, of conſolation. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde Chriſt with diligent eyes vpon the Croſſe, and thou ſhalt finde hid therein ſo great and ſo wonderfull treaſures, that they will cauſe thée to crye out &amp; ſay with Saint Paule: O the dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ryches, of the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and knowledge of God. Thou ſhalt finde alſo good cauſe to maruell, if thou conſider his
<pb facs="tcp:21583:49"/>
great power and might whiche he ſhewed in his paſſion: for ſo muche as thereby he ouercame the diuell, and being exalted on the Croſſe, he drew all things to him, as he ſaide before, &amp; dying he deſtroyed death, triumphing ouer the world and hell.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt likewiſe finde good cauſe to wonder, if thou marke well the iuſtice he obſerued in his paſſion and death, in that he would not our ſinnes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould remayne without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence and ſatiſfaction, and by it giue remiſſion and pardon of them, and that more fréely and fully, then of our part was
<pb facs="tcp:21583:50"/>
due or deſerued. And by howe much more thou art willing to conſider &amp; ſearch out the ſecrets of the Croſſe, ſo muche the more high myſteries ſhall be reuealed vnto thée, and cauſe thée not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to maruell, but alſo to be greatly amaſed. And then ſhalte thou knowe that Saint Paule the Apoſtle ſpake not without great cauſe, when he ſayde: He would preache none other, nor would learne to knowe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, but Ieſus Chriſt and him crucified.</p>
               <p>By this then hitherto ſaid, thou mayſt gather and perceiue how copious matter thou haſte to
<pb facs="tcp:21583:50"/>
maruell and wonder at, when thou art in this maner diſpoſed to meditate vpon the death and paſſion of thy Redéemer. All whiche the better to retayne in memorye, thou mayeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and bring them to theſe poyntes.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, to conſider the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite highneſſe and maieſtie of thy Lorde that ſuffered for thée. The ſeconde is, the ſeruile and baſe eſtate of them for whom he ſuffered. Thirdly, the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tormentes and iniuries which he ſuffered. Fourthly, the wiſedome, power, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice which he declared in his
<pb facs="tcp:21583:51"/>
bleſſed paſſion and death. Theſe things in maner before ſpecified and others that may happen to come into thy remembraunce whiles thou art in thy medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if thou conſider them as thou oughteſt attentiuely, ſhall miniſter occaſion vnto thée, greatly to maruell and wonder at this diuine myſterie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A declaration of the ſeuenth manner of meditation, which is by way of hope and reioyſing.</head>
               <p>The ſeuenth manner of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation we ſayde was by waye of reioyſing and hope: Whiche
<pb facs="tcp:21583:51"/>
kinde of meditation is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie alſo ſometime to vſe. For when a man ſhal with him ſelfe conſider, howe great the wickedneſſe and euill of ſinne is, howe odious it is, and howe muche it diſpleaſeth God, ſéeing for the due puniſhment thereof, and for to repaye and repayre the great loſſes it had cauſed in the worlde, our Lorde him ſelf came downe from heauen, and after ſo great trauels and paynefull life, at the laſte he would ſuffer ſo bitter paſſion and death: And when he ſhall likewiſe call to minde, that he hath runne and fallen into his
<pb facs="tcp:21583:52"/>
haynous euill and ſinfulneſſe, not only once, but many times and in diuerſe ſortes: he ſhall then reſt ſo ſad and diſmayed, that he ſhall néede of ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall helpe for to comfort him, that he diſpayre not in him ſelfe when he remembreth that he ſhall appeare before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of the fearfull iudge, to yéelde the account of all his life. To remember this, it hath made not onely many ſinners to feare and tremble, but alſo iuſte men and perſons of holy life, as is to be ſéene by thoſe wordes whiche that iuſte m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Iob ſpake: That euen as the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:52"/>
maryner feareth when he ſeeth the ſwelling waues of the ſeas, ſo he feared God. And this feare doth ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grow to a man, when he remembreth the latter day: becauſe he knoweth that to be true whiche is ſpoken by the Prophet Dauid, that no man liuing ſhall be iuſtified before God. Nowe if the iuſte ſhall ſcarſly be ſaued, as Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſayth, howe ſhall the ſinner do, whiche remembreth howe greatly and howe many wayes he hath offended God, for the whiche he hath deſerued to be condemned, not once, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:53"/>Therfore, good brother, when thou ſhalt find thy ſelfe to ſtand in like feare and diſpayre, one of the beſt remedies that thou canſt haue to comfort thy ſelfe and pull vp thy hart againe, is, to remember and bethinke thy ſelfe what thy moſte mercyfull Sauiour hath done and ſuffred for thée. The very ſame remedie the prophet Dauid ſignified that he founde, when he ſayde: My ſoule is troubled within me ſelf, and therfore will I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me of thée in the lande of Iordan, and Hermon, and in the litle hill. In which wordes he teacheth vs that the remedie
<pb facs="tcp:21583:53"/>
a man may haue, féeling himſelf ſorowfull, ſad, and troubled in ſpirit, for the remembraunce of his ſins, or for any other thing: is to remember him ſelf agayne what Chriſte did for vs in his life, which is ſignified by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land of Iordan and Hermon where he was baptiſed, preached, and was conuerſant. And likewiſe to call to minde that whiche he ſuffered, which is noted by the litle hill, that is to ſay, at Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarie, where he was crucified. When therefore thou ſhalte ſée thy ſelfe troubled in minde, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, ſad, and afflicted, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the bottomleſſe pitte of
<pb facs="tcp:21583:54"/>
thy ſinnes, of thy blindneſſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and of the myſerie preſent wherein thou findeſt thy ſelfe: turne then thy conſideration to thinke vpon the déepneſſe of the mercy of thy moſte gracious Lorde, who for thée and thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation came downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and was made man, and for thy ſake was crucified and died. Conſider therfore the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfull redemption he hath lefte for thée, and that if thou haue offended muche, he hath muche ſatiſfied for thée, if thou be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; diligent to know how by his ſatiſfaction to helpe thy ſelf. If the multitude of the ſinnes
<pb facs="tcp:21583:54"/>
thou haſt committed do feare thée, bicauſe thou haſt thereby iuſtly deſerued to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned, comforte thy ſelfe in thinking howe he hath fully ſatiſfied the iuſtice of God, becauſe thou ſhuldeſt participate of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. If thou faynt, diſpaire, or els miſcruſt thy owne pouertie, and the ſmall good ſeruice thou haſt done towards god: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy ſelfe of the great riches and merites he hath lefte thée by meanes of his paſſion, in the which thou mayeſt chiefly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and put all thy truſt. But yet ſo that thou fayle not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour thy ſelfe to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb facs="tcp:21583:55"/>
of thy power to ſerue and pleaſe him. And remember alſo howe that Lorde which in time to come ſhall be thy iudge, is at this preſent thy aduocate to god the Father eternall, to whom he ſhoweth thoſe his fiue bleſſed wounds, with the markes and ſignes wherewith it was his pleaſure to be ſéene after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: becauſe his heauenly father ſhould thereby be incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to haue mercy vpon vs, and to vs they ſhould be a teſtimony of the loue he bare vs. Whiche both the one and the other ſhall giue thée great occaſion &amp; holde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt of hope and comfort.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:55"/>Moreouer conſider the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Sacraments he hath left thée in this Churche, as ſtrong effectuous medicins and ſalues, for all the wounds, ſores, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities which thou canſt haue.</p>
               <p>Remember alſo that, euen as the Apoſtle ſayth, better and lowder crieth the blood whiche Chriſt ſhed, then the blood of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel. Becauſe the blood of Abel aſked vengeance agaynſt his brother that ſhed it: but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood of Chriſte aſketh mercy and pardon for them that ſhed it, and alſo for al them that truſt in it. Sée therefore howe great hope and ioy thou mayeſt
<pb facs="tcp:21583:56"/>
receiue in vſing of this kinde of meditation vpon the holy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And the order thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to obſerue herein, is, that when thou art diſpoſed to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate vpon that which thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer hath ſuffered, then aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly accounte and thinke all was done for thy ſake, and that the plentifull fruite &amp; benefite which by meanes of his paſſion and death he hath purchaſed, was for thée and to thy behoue, and he would that thou ſhuldeſt be partaker thereof, if the fault be not in thy ſelfe. So that thou mayeſt aſſuredly beléeue, that his tormentes be thine, that his
<pb facs="tcp:21583:56"/>
teares and ſorowes are thine, the infinite price of his blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhedding to be thine, and finally that all his death and paſſion is thine. For as we haue ſaid, for thée he ſuffred, and he gratiouſly would thou ſhouldeſt be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the fruite thereof, ſo to vnderſtand what precious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thou haſt layde vp in him. Whiche conſideration ſhall ſo eaſe thée of thy payne and feare, and giue thée ſo great hope and gladneſſe, that it ſhall cauſe thée to ſaye with Saint Paule: God forbidde that I ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce or glory in any thing els, but in the Croſſe of my Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:21583:57"/>
Ieſu Chriſt. And worthily, for in it thou haſt an infinite trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, by meanes whereof thou haſt obtayned ſaluation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation betwéene God and thée, and thy ſinnes be forgiuen thée, thou art receiued for the ſonne of god, the gate of heauen is opened vnto thée, and with it and by it all goodneſſe in one heape is caſt vnto thée. Sée then what cauſe thou haſt to reioyce and leape for gladneſſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this. But here I muſt not forget to aduiſe thée, that when after this ſort thou haſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate vpon this holy myſterie, thou muſt remember that this
<pb facs="tcp:21583:57"/>
hope and ioye which thou ſhalt féele in finding thy ſelfe ſo enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and full of ſpirituall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: they cauſe thée not to wax colde, negligent, and ſlouthful in good workes, but rather that therby thou be ſtirred &amp; pricked forward in feruent and earneſt loue of God, and to ſerue him: Aſwell to ſhew thy ſelfe, as good reaſon is, thankfull to thy bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, as alſo leſt he take away agayne from thée the ſame his giftes and riches, as it hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to others for their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe and negligence.</p>
               <p>And thus much touching this maner of meditation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21583:58"/>
               <head>A declaration of the eight ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meditation, by the way of loue.</head>
               <p>The eight kinde and ſorte of meditation vpon the paſſion, is by way of loue, whiche we haue placed here laſtly, becauſe according to the mind of Saint Paule: Like as the ende of the commaundementes is charitie or loue procéeding from a pure heart: So alſo the principall purpoſe and ende of meditation vpon this holy myſterie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is, that the ſoule may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne inflamed in the loue of God. According to that which the holy prophet Dauid vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode
<pb facs="tcp:21583:58"/>
when he ſayd: In my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation the fyre ſhall be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that is to ſay, my ſoule ſhall be inflamed with the fyre of the loue of God and true charitie. And among all meditations in the which this heauenly fyre is kindled, the chiefeſt is this of the paſſion and death of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer. Bicauſe if there be any thing that hath force to drawe the loue of one man to loue an other, it is to knowe that he is loued of the other: and ſo there can not be a thing in the worlde more apte to drawe the heart of a Chriſtian to loue God, then to conſider how God
<pb facs="tcp:21583:59"/>
firſt loued him, the whiche he may very well vnderſtande by that whiche he did and ſuffered for him. And if it be the greateſt ſigne that a friend can ſhowe of that loue he beareth towardes an other, to giue his owne life for him, as he our Lord him ſelf ſayth, this ſigne then haue we moſt manifeſtly of the loue he bare vs, for that his will was to giue his moſt precious lyfe for vs, or rather as Saint Paul concludeth, a greater ſigne can we not haue of his innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue, then to knowe his will was to offer him ſelfe vnto death, euen the death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:59"/>
and that not only for his frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, but alſo for his enemies. If then thou were negligent, ſlouthfull, and cold to loue God before thou kneweſt how much he loued thée: nowe thou doeſt knowe it by ſuche and ſo many ſignes and argumentes, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to him which hath ſo loued thée. Call to minde in this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie how ſtreatly thou art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of al the whole Trinitie, ſéeing the father ſo muche loued thée, that he gaue his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne vnto death for thée. Remember wel thoſe words of the Euangeliſt S. Iohn, which ſaith in this maner: So God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:21583:60"/>
the worlde that for it he gaue his onely begotten ſonne. In which wordes thou mayeſt knowe the greatnes of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of whom thou art ſo belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and that is the Father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie maker of heauen and of earth: and alſo the greatnes of his loue wherewith he loued thée is manyfeſt, by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the gifte whiche he gaue thée, and that is his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne, who hath the ſame like infinite power, bounty and maieſtie with the father. And this ſuche a ſonne he hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly giuen thée, that taking thy humanitie or manhood, he
<pb facs="tcp:21583:60"/>
might dye in the ſame for thée and redéeme thée, in ſuche ſorte as the Apoſtle ſayth, God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not his owne ſonne, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don vs his miſerable ſeruants. O ineſtimable loue, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then any vnderſtanding can comprehende. And likewiſe the loue of the Sonne was nothing leſſe then this of the Father, in that he came downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and was incarnate for thée, ſpente hys lyfe and dyed for thée, that by ſuche meanes he might in diuers ſortes be giuen to thée: In byrth as thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, in life as thy comfort, in his laſt Supper as thy foode,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:61"/>
in death as price for thée, in heauen as a rewarde for thée. And as the loue of the Father and the Sonne was towardes thée, ſo was the loue of the holy Ghoſt, who willed &amp; wrought together with the father and the ſonne, thy ſaluation &amp; redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now the moſt bleſſed and glorious Trinitie hath ſo loued thée, how canſt thou be ſo ſlacke in re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring to him loue for loue, ſéeing that loue can not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed but with loue.</p>
               <p>And if thou vnderſtande not this excéeding loue of God by other benefites whiche he hath done for thée, as in thy creation
<pb facs="tcp:21583:61"/>
and conſeruation: conſider yet what thou haſt receiued of him in thy reparation and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; then ſhalt thou perceiue how true thoſe words be which he ſpake by the prophet Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: With perpetual loue haue I loued thée, and therefore haue I drawen thée to me in hauing mercy vpon thée. Theſe be the ſharpe arrowes which the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophet Dauid ſpeaketh of, ſufficient to pearce anye hard hart. Theſe be the new warres which the ſcripture ſpeaketh of, that a king is from heauen ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to ſubdue and conquer men of the earth: Differing from the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:62"/>
firſt, which he made with thret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and feare. Theſe be the ropes of Adam, and the cordes of charitie with which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet O ſay ſayth he would draw men vnto him. Becauſe if they will worke according to the vſe of reaſon, which they haue in reſpect they be reaſonable men, they ought not to be more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable then brute beaſtes, who ſuffer them ſelues to be drawen with ropes and halters in finding them ſelues forced and conſtrayned to loue ſuch as loueth them.</p>
               <p>When thou therefore ſhalte meditate vppon the death and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:62"/>
paſſion of thy Redéemer, let the principall ende of thy trauell be to be rauiſhed in the loue of ſuch a Lorde that hath ſo loued thée, and by ſo many profes hath wel declared his loue towards thée: and aſſure thy ſelfe that al thoſe ſtripes and bloodye woundes which thou beholdeſt in him, be voyces crying and teſtifying his deare and true loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes thée. Beholde him vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Croſſe thruſt through with a ſpeare, and thou ſhalte perceiue how he prouoketh and forceth thée to loue him. His féete ſo nayled do ſhowe that he will tarie for thée, if thou wilte
<pb facs="tcp:21583:63"/>
returne &amp; come agayne to him. His armes ſo ſtretched do ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that he deſireth to embrace thée. His head ſo bowed downe, doth ſignifie that he will giue thée the kiſſe of grace. That ſide of his opened with a ſpere, doth manifeſtly ſhew that he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to giue thée a place in his hart, where thou mayſt reſt thy ſelfe quietly &amp; ſurely. And what other thing might he do for thée, which he hath not done? And what other thing doth he more require of thée, but in that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging this his loue, thou anſwere him agayne with thy loue? O moſte ſwéete Ieſu the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:63"/>
true louer of men, what is he, if he well conſider this and know it, that can denie the thing thou requireſt of him, and for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cauſes is due vnto thée? And howe can any man excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to loue thée, béeing pricked forwarde and prouoked with ſo many motions and ſwéete cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of thy diuine loue?</p>
               <p>Be not therefore, my good bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vnthankfull, nor ſo dull to vnderſtande this his ſo great loue, for the which it ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houe thy hart to melt euen as the wax, whenſoeuer thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreſt that he loued thée firſt, and that he waſhed thée
<pb facs="tcp:21583:64"/>
with his precious blood. Denie him not the tribute of loue thou oweſt him, for although he haue forgiuen thée other thy debtes, yet this he will not diſcharge or acquite thée of, but rather affirmeth that he came to put fyre on the earth, and woulde that it ſhould burne continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And in figure of this he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded in the olde lawe, that the fyre ſhoulde ſtande alwayes kindled vppon his altar. The whiche is not ſo muche ment of the materiall fyre, as of the ſpirituall, which is our loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and that he would ſhould alwayes burne vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:64"/>
altar of our heart, becauſe that ſacrifice is alwayes accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him whiche is offered with ſuche fyre. And becauſe this maye be nouriſhed and maynteined, it behoueth that euen as the Prieſtes in the olde Lawe did bring of all ſortes of materiall wood for to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne and kéepe in that mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall fyre: So thou muſte be carefull to laye on that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall woode, and that is of the Croſſe, of the whippes and roddes, of the ſpeare and other inſtrumentes of that holy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whervpon if thou deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditate, it ſhall ſtande thée
<pb facs="tcp:21583:65"/>
in ſtead of wood moſt fit to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle thy deuotion and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</p>
               <p>Let the concluſion therefore be of that which we haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſaide: that in meditating after this maner vpon this holy myſterie, and knowing by it how much thou art bounde (as is declared) for that whiche he hath ſuffred for thée, and muche more for the loue in whiche he ſuffred, &amp; that was muche more then his exceſſiue tormentes: thou muſt render and yéelde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the beſt recompence thou canſt, whiche is but loue for loue. And this thou ſhalt do, if
<pb facs="tcp:21583:65"/>
thou be minde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull alwayes to haue thy heart inflamed in loue towardes him, &amp; melting with the meditation and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of his tender loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thée.</p>
               <p>Thus then as thou ſeeſt we haue declared vnto thée all the foreſayde orders of meditation vpon the paſſon: but yet for thy better exerciſe thou mayſt helpe thy ſelfe with theſe aduiſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21583:66"/>
               <head>¶ Certayne aduiſes which may be obſerued in the ſayd me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, or in any other.</head>
               <p>NOwe thou haſt ſéene all the aforeſaide kinds and ſorts of meditation, it doth remayne for a concluſion and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe inſtructions, to giue thée briefly certayne adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whereby thou mayeſt with more fruite and ſwéeteneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thy ſelfe in the ſame. The whiche maye not onely helpe thée to meditate vpon the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Chriſtes paſſion, but alſo in anye other meditation elſe vppon his life, or prayers,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:66"/>
whiche thou doeſt intende to mark. And in theſe aduiſes thou ſhalt learne thrée things. The firſt, what order thou muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue before thou entreſt into thy meditation. Secondarily, the maner of procéeding in thy meditation. And the third, what thou ſhouldeſt doe when thou haſte finiſhed thy meditation.</p>
               <p>The firſt aduiſe to be had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy meditation, is to be learned of the wiſe man, who counſelleth thée that before thou pray, thou prepare thy minde or heart. Which preparation conſiſteth in endeuouring to go about this holy exerciſe with
<pb facs="tcp:21583:67"/>
the greateſt clenneſſe and pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart and mind thou canſt. For euen as we ſhould ſée alwayes that the veſſell be well waſhed &amp; cleane, in whiche we purpoſe to put any kinde of precious liquor: Agreable to that which our Sauiour ſayth: That men vſe not to put newe wine into olde bottels. So alſo to receiue the newe wine or muſt of that heauenly loue, and precious liquor of grace, deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and other giftes that the mercy of God is willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe vpon vs: it is neceſſarie that the veſſell which ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, that is the ſoule, be
<pb facs="tcp:21583:67"/>
pure and made freſhe. And the more waſhed and cleane it ſhall be, ſo muche the feruenter and better diſpoſition it ſhall haue, to receiue more aboundantly this moſte precious liquor. It ſhall be therefore good, before thou beginne to meditate, that thou examine thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, and make clene and ſwéepe the duſt and filthe whiche thou findeſt therein, the whiche commonly are wont to be veniall ſinnes, that is to ſay, vayne thoughtes, idle wordes, negligences, and other like things which do eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleaue and ſticke faſt in vs, or rather let and take away
<pb facs="tcp:21583:68"/>
that perfect holynes and puritie with which a man ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour earneſtly to appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſight of God. This thou mayeſt do in aſking God hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pardon for thy particuler faults, which thou ſhalt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted: for which and for other generall defectes that thou canſt not remember, thou mayeſt ſaye at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy meditation, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion, with the hymne of the holy Ghoſt, or one Pater noſter, and an Aue Maria, or ſome other prayer, as ſhal ſéeme beſte for thy purpoſe, deſiring God of his grace to ſpende that
<pb facs="tcp:21583:68"/>
time in meditation, with ſuche attention, reuerence, and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as thou art bound to, and ſhall be moſt acceptable to his diuine maieſtie.</p>
               <p>The ſecond aduiſe is, that thou endeuour ſo to ſet thy things in order before thou pray, that thy thought and care of that which thou haſt after to do, moleſt and trouble thée not, or let thée in thy prayer. The whiche thou mayeſt do, if thou firſt diſpatche all thinges thou haſte to doe, if thou mayeſt commodiouſly: or elſe in making accounte with thy ſelfe, not to haue any other care or buſineſſe in the worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:69"/>
but that whiche thou goeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and that is the greteſt and chiefeſt thou canſt do, if that vpon thine obedience there be none other thing appoynted thée in charge. Finally thou muſte endeuour to be frée and ridde cleane from all other cares and thoughtes, when thou giueſt thy ſelfe to this exerciſe: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that when the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch Abraham went with his ſonne Iſahac to offer him in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, when they came to the foote of the hill where he ſhould ſacrifice him, he ſayd to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts that wayted vpon him, Tarie there beneath a while,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:69"/>
till I come agayne vnto you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we haue prayed to God: Euen ſo likewiſe ſhall it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that thou commaunde thy thoughtes and cares to tary without, when thou goeſt to the place where thou muſte offer to God the ſacrifice of thy prayer. As we reade a certen holy man did alwayes at the Churche doore euery time he went in to pray, and then he made his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer with more fruite of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; comfort, when the ſoule ſo reſted in ſolitary maner to it ſelfe, ridde and diſcharged from all other impertinent cares and thoughts, ſo that he might truly
<pb facs="tcp:21583:70"/>
ſay as the ſpouſe in the Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: I to my welbeloued, and my welbeloued to me. In ſuche ſort that for the time preſent ſhe harken to none other voyce or companie.</p>
               <p>The thirde counſell is, that thou giue thy ſelfe to this holye exerciſe with a right and perfect intent: for that there be diuers reſpectes and endes with which many go to prayer and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſome to the ende they may receiue: ſome to taſte of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all comforte, whiche at other times they haue proued: Some to deſire of God ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar grace, gifte, or vertue, which
<pb facs="tcp:21583:70"/>
many deſire, knowing that to be the principall meane to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne it: Some to repreſent before God as their moſte mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull father, their trauels, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and temptations, their ſpirituall and corporall neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, deſiring to be deliuered from them. Finallye, other ſome goe to praye, to fulfill a good vſe and cuſtome they haue euery daye ſo to exerciſe them ſelfe, or becauſe they be vppon their obedience ſo commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to doo. And albeit theſe and ſuche other like cauſes may be both good and laudable: yet the principall purpoſe and ende
<pb facs="tcp:21583:71"/>
of this thy exerciſe: muſt be for pure loue and only for the glory of God. So that thy owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer neceſſitie or néede, or thine owne comfort, gaine, and profit ought not ſo much to moue thée, as the ende &amp; deſire thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt haue in all thinges to ſéeke for the glory of God &amp; to pleaſe him, euen as the Apoſtle coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth thée, that al things which we doo, be for the glory of God. This than being thy principall ſcope and intent, it ſhall cauſe thée with chéerefull hart &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling minde to meditate or pray, conſideryng that God woulde that thoſe giftes which his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes
<pb facs="tcp:21583:71"/>
doo offer vnto him, and the ſeruice that thy doo, be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and done chéerefully &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. And this wiſe thou ſhalt alwayes finde fruit and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of minde in thy prayer and meditation, if perchaunce thou finde thy ſelfe dry without ſpirituall taſte in it.</p>
               <p>Theſe thrée aduiſes which we haue hitherto declared of the cleanneſſe of conſcience &amp; quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of minde from all other bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, therby to come with more attentiue pure mind to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, may helpe this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou begin to pray. And the other thrée no leſſe neceſſarie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:72"/>
are to bée vſed duryng the tyme of thy prayer: of the which the firſt is, that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries which thou doeſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate vpon, be not curiouſly ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into of thée, either with too much ſpeculation, in going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute ſubtillye to ſéeke out di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers points, argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons &amp; imaginations, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to vnderſtande them, where as in déede it doth rather diſtract the vnderſtanding &amp; hynder de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, according to that which the wyſe man ſayeth: That he which is inquiſitiue of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, ſhall be oppreſſed of hys glory. And the heauenly ſpouſe
<pb facs="tcp:21583:72"/>
ſayeth to the ſoule his ſpouſe: Turne away thy eyes from me bicauſe they make me fly away: which is to be vnderſtande by curious eyes, with which ſhée woulde beholde him in prayer. Wherfore endeuour to ſtand in it, with a ſimple &amp; humble ſight of the miſtery which thou ſhalt thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beholding it inward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, or outwardly, as though thou ſaweſt it preſent before thée. To the whiche it maye helpe thée to haue before thy eye the image of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſterie which thou ſhalt meditate vppon, and with the onely ſyght and regarde of it outwardlye content thy ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:73"/>
withoute buſie diſcourſings of the minde, or imaginations vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other thinges impertinent. Nor yet muſt thou doe any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to thy wil, that is, to wreſt out as it were by force ſome teares or ſenſible deuotion: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all this hurteth, healeth, and helpeth, little to that thou goeſt about. Therefore ſtudie to meditate quietly and cloſely the pointes which are ſette before thée, abyding with ſilence and hope, as the ſcripture ſaieth, the grace that God ſhall vouchſafe to giue thée.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde aduiſe is, that if in meditation thou ſhalt fynde
<pb facs="tcp:21583:73"/>
thy ſelfe ouer drie and without taſt of deuotion, or elſe to much diſtract with diuers cogitations and wauering of the minde: thou muſt not therfore be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, nor yet ceaſſe to goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde in thy exerciſe, but in ſuch caſe thou mayeſt helpe thy ſelf with ſome colloquies &amp; talk with thy Lorde God, to whom thou ſhalte open thy diſtraction and wearineſſe, deſiring him to helpe thée to dryue away thoſe buſie flyes of thoughtes and i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations which drawe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, to waſt the ſwéete oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy deuotion.</p>
               <p>If thou wilt this doe, with
<pb facs="tcp:21583:74"/>
that faythe, humilitie, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience as is requiſite thereto: God which regardeth and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the prayers of the humble, will haue compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thou doeſt ſuffer, and will viſite and comfort thée preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or after when it ſhalbe expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for thée.</p>
               <p>For ſo we reade in the booke of Geneſis, that Abraham offring on a tyme ſacrifice to God of certayne beaſtes which he had killed, there came byrds to eate the fleſhe of thoſe beaſtes, and to lette the ſacrifice: ſo that he was troubled and occupyed a good part of the day in driuing
<pb facs="tcp:21583:74"/>
away thoſe byrdes, that they ſhould not come néere the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, wherby he deſerued of God to bée viſited and comforted with a quiet and pleaſaunt viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which he ſent him, wherein he receaued a great reuelation. The which is a figure of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde that our Lorde God is wont to gyue afterwardes to them who buſily driue away the little byrdes of temptation and lothſomeneſſe, which commonly happen to them that offer the ſacrifice of prayer. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wyſe man ſayeth that the end of prayer is better than the beginning.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:75"/>Becauſe that albeit a man in the beginning féeleth him ſelfe colde &amp; diſtract, yet afterwardes in the diſcourſe of his meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he gathereth himſelfe to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; calling his wits to him, begynneth to be feruent, &amp; fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth conſolation. And if ſo be he fayleth of this at one tyme, yet it is ſupplyed at an other.</p>
               <p>The thirde aduiſe is, that if contrariwyſe it happen thée to finde deuotion and ſwéete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at the firſt or ſecond point of that thou haſte to meditate vppon, than ſtaye thy ſelfe in conſideration of that as longe as thy deuotion ſhal endure and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:75"/>
the inwarde féelyng thereof, without hauyng any doubte or ſcruple at all for not paſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further to meditate vpon the other poyntes remayning. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it auayleth more to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate a fewe thinges well with deuotion and fruyte, then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny without taſte and ſwéete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And chiefely that thoſe poyntes which for this cauſe are lefte vnmeditated vppon at one tyme, maye bée taken in hand another tyme, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced in thy meditations fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. And of this that maye be well vnderſtand which ſaint Paul affirmeth: that it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:21583:76"/>
to ſpeake fiue wordes with a ſpirituall féeling or edifying, then ten thouſande without at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and ſpirit.</p>
               <p>With theſe thrée aduiſes thou mayſt ſerue thy ſelfe, and which I truſt ſhall be profitable vnto thée, for the tyme thou arte in thy meditation: and after thou haſt done, thou mayeſt vſe the other thrée which we ſhall here declare vnto thée.</p>
               <p>Let therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt aduiſe be, that when in prayer God ſhall vouchſafe of his goodneſſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due thée with ſome inſpiration and deuotion, or other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar gift or grace: that thou then
<pb facs="tcp:21583:76"/>
endeuour to kéepe it diligently, and not ſuffer thy ſelfe to bée colde ſtrayghtwayes after thy meditation wyth vnprofitable thoughtes, imaginations or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtractions or contrary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupations: but rather endeuour to walke all day as cloſely with thy wyttes gathered to thy ſelfe as thou canſt, remembring to thy ſelfe often that which in thy prayer was commicate vnto thée, and of thy good purpoſe and deſire which thou foundeſt in it: Becauſe it maye ſo reſt more fixed in thy mynde, and to the entent that deuotion and feruencie which thou receiuedſt
<pb facs="tcp:21583:77"/>
whiles thou diddeſt pray be not loſt. And after this ſorte thou ſhalt fulfill that which the wiſe man counſelleth thée, ſaying: With all diligence kéepe thy hart, becauſe of it procedeth life. And alſo it ſhall auayle thée to go all day with ſuche care and diligence, becauſe thou ſhalt not ſo eaſily fall into ſinne as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times thou wert vſed to do. And bicauſe God maye giue thée ſometime in the daye that deuotion and conſolation, the which was not giuen thée at the time of thy prayer, as it hath often happened to many: This diligence and care doth likewiſe
<pb facs="tcp:21583:77"/>
profite thée, in that thou mayeſt be the readier and better diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make thy prayers and meditations afterwards. For euen as water which is already hoat may be ſo kept in the ſame heate with a litle fire, the which if ye ſuffer it once to be loſte, it becommeth colde, and is not without more paynes agayne made hoat: So likewiſe chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth it to the ſoule, in preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or ſuffering it to looſe the heate whiche it once receyued. And to this end the bleſſed men in times paſte did vſe often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the daye thoſe kinde of prayers whiche in Latin they
<pb facs="tcp:21583:78"/>
termed <hi>Iaculatoriae,</hi> which were no more but certayne ſhort ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations or lyfting vppe of the minde and ſwéete ſighes, which they ſpéedily ſhotte vp to God, that by them as it were wyth certayne ſtyckes layed to the fyre, they mayntayned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued that heate ſtill which they had before receaued. And this a man maye doe eaſily al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be occupyed about di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other buſines &amp; exerciſes.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde aduiſe is, that ſometime in the wéeke or when thou beſt maye, thou fynde a tyme to examine thy ſelfe, and to ſée whether thou haue gone
<pb facs="tcp:21583:78"/>
forwarde, or gotten any profite of thy praying. And when thou ſhalt ſée that thou haſt profited nothing at all, nor founde in thy ſelfe any difference of one tyme better than an other: then exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne and trye out from what cauſe it procéeded, &amp; thou ſhalte alwayes finde, that it happened of ſome fault or lack in thy ſelf, eyther for not mortifying thy ſelfe, which is neceſſary in this exerciſe, or for not doing it with due care &amp; diligence, or for not folowing the aduiſes which are giuen thée, or for ſome other negligence of thyne owne.</p>
               <p>And for what cauſe ſoeuer thou
<pb facs="tcp:21583:79"/>
ſhalt vnderſtand that this ſmall encreaſe of deuotion and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hath procéeded, procure yet to remedie the ſame, and make amendes for the time to come of the faulte paſſed. And that thou mayeſt vnderſtande the better whether thou haſt gotten any fruite or no of thy prayer, thou muſt note that which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices or yong beginners in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer or other their exerciſes haue chiefly to regarde, which is, the mortification of their paſſions, their ſenſuall appetites and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and to purge and clenſe well their ſoules. And thoſe which haue further entred and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:79"/>
procéeded, oughte chieflye to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and care to attayne the vertue which they lacke, and to increaſe and augment the ſame, ſpecially their charitie. And thoſe which be more auncient as it were, and more forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entred into perfection, haue to trauell for the perfect vnion and conformitie with God in making one ſpirite with him as muche as ſhall be poſſible for them, although ſometime the exerciſe of the one of theſe may attende to the ende and effect of the other. According to this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe then you may vnderſtande when you haue profited more,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:80"/>
or leſſe, or nothing at all, and ſo ſtudie to remedie that ſhall bée conuenient.</p>
               <p>The thyrde and laſte aduiſe is, that although perchaunce it ſéeme in long tyme thou haſt lyttle profited, or that thou art nothing giuen to this exercyſe of meditation, nor féeleſt in thy ſelfe that deuotion, nor ſuch taſt therein as thou wouldeſt: Yet oughteſt thou not therefore to diſpayre or ſlacke to procéede forwarde. Becauſe that euen as in other good workes, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce is it that maketh all perfect, &amp; crowneth euery ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue with rewarde: So alſo it
<pb facs="tcp:21583:80"/>
happeneth in this ſo holye &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a worke of prayer, that by howe muche the more thou ſhalt perſeuer and continue thy good exerciſe therein, ſo muche thou ſhalt the more merite, and God ſhal giue thée in proceſſe of tyme ſo muche the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and rewarde, as thou haſt felte thy ſelfe drye and faynt in the beginning.</p>
               <p>For oftentimes God permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that ſome are founde drye and bare of all deuotion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all taſte and ſauourineſſe in theyr meditation: to the intent that howe much the more they labour and trauell to perſeuer
<pb facs="tcp:21583:81"/>
and continue in the ſame, ſo muche the more comforte and fruite they receiue afterwards in rewarde of their perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. For euen as God did in the creation of the worlde firſt frame the earth to be hard and dry, and then couered it with waters, that ſo it might fructifie and produce plantes of diuers gréene and fruitfull trées: ſo alſo the ſame our Lord God permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſome ſoules to be founde in their prayers drye and barren, without taſt or ſauour of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at al, that by their patience in perſeueraunce of this trauell of minde and lothſomneſſe, they
<pb facs="tcp:21583:81"/>
come afterwards to bring forth faire fruite and plentifull of muche vertue and grace which ſhall be beſtowed on them. And that God doth ſignifie vnto vs in ſaying by the Prophet Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: I remembred her becauſe ſhe did follow me in the deſertes and wildernes, and in that land that is not ſowen. Which is to vnderſtande of the ſoule that perſeuered and continued in ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after God, although ſhée felte her ſelfe drye and deſert, without féeling or taſte of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or conſolation. And the ſame affirmeth Chriſt our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer in the Goſpell, ſaying:
<pb facs="tcp:21583:82"/>
In your patience ye ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe your ſoules. Take more courage then, good Chriſtian brother, and let not thy drineſſe or vnſauerie lothſomeneſſe, or payne which thou féeleſt in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation or prayer, cauſe thée to turne backe and leaue of thy godly purpoſe: Leaſt it happen to thée as to the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, who deſerued not to enter into the deſired land of promiſe, becauſe they had not patience in their famine &amp; hunger, with other payne and trauell whiche they ſuffered in the wilderneſſe. Endeuour rather to followe that perſeueraunce of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb facs="tcp:21583:82"/>
of Cananie, who although ſhe ſawe her ſelfe not regarded, and ſhaken off from Chriſt, ſhe did not for all that miſtruſt, nor ceaſſed her ſute or petition: and ſo deſerued to obtayne muche more of him then that whiche ſhe aſked or deſired. And the like thou mayeſt well hope ſhal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto thée, if thou wilt haue the lyke patience and truſt in God, which ſayth, he that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth vnto the end ſhalbe ſaued.</p>
               <p>To conclude, helpe thy ſelfe therefore with theſe thrée ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries of aduiſes and counſells, which I woulde thou ſhouldeſt alwayes haue freſhe in thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:83"/>
and to practiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye one of them in their due place as ſhall bée néedefull, as well before prayer, in prayer, as after: and thereby (and that principallye by Gods grace, which he ſhall vouchſafe to geue thée) thou ſhalte bée able with great fruite and comfort to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thy ſelfe in theſe medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the bleſſed paſſion folowing, as the holy Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes declare the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21583:83"/>
               <head>Certayne godly Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and prayers vpon the Paſſion of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:84"/>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Perfundit caput vnguentis pia faemina Chriſti:</l>
                  <l>Atque pedibus tergens crinibus ipſa fuis.</l>
               </q>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:84"/>
                  <head>¶The firſt meditation is of the Supper that was made to Chriſt our Lord in Bethania, ſixe days before his paſsion, which is the Saboth before Palmeſunday. Concerning which ye may meditate theſe poynts following.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 HOwe that Chriſt oure redéemer comming vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Bethania ſixe dayes before his Paſſion, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the houſe of Symon Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſus, where at that tyme was Lazarus &amp; his two ſiſters Martha and Magdalen, and it is to be ſuppoſed, that the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:21583:85"/>
bleſſed virgin his mother was there alſo.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider with what chéerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and diligence Martha ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the table, and that moſt feruent loue &amp; deuotion of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Magdalene: who taking a veſſell of Alabaſter full of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious oyntment, powred it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the head and féete of hir be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued maiſter, and wyped hys féete with her heare, and howe that the houſe was filled wyth the ſauour of that ſwéete oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Remember alſo howe the traitour Iudas murmured that Magdalene had ſo beſtowed an
<pb facs="tcp:21583:85"/>
oyntment of ſuche great value: And how our moſt gracious Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu defended her, and prayſed the woorke of ſo greate charitie and deuotion that ſhe had done. In the whiche was ſignifyed hys death and buriall that was at hande.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>The prayer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> My GOD and Lorde, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt other ſeruices and ſacrifices which are acceptable to thée, and which thou requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of vs, thou haſte declared howe the ſacrifice of laude and prayſe pleaſeth thée. Wherfore
<pb facs="tcp:21583:86"/>
knowing howe muche all men are debtours to thée for ſo great giftes and benefites receyued of thy moſt liberall hande: I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to offer to thée the ſame ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. My ſoule therefore, moſt ſwéete Ieſu, maketh adoration and giueth thankes to thée, and all my powers within me bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thy moſt holy name, for all the works which thou haſt done in the courſe of thy bleſſed lyfe, &amp; for the innumerable ſorowes, reproches and tormentes which thou haſt ſuffred in thy paſſion, which thou wouldeſt ſhoulde be alwaies imprinted in my hart. And firſt I laude &amp; prayſe thée,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:86"/>
that knowing the nearer thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull death was at hand, and for the whiche thoſe thy deare friendes that loued thée ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ſhould be in great ſorowe and ſadneſſe: it was thy godly pleaſure firſt to chéere and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertayne them, in ſupping with them in Bethanie, where thoſe two moſte deuoute ſiſters Mary and Martha declared the pure loue thy bare vnto thée. I beſéeche thée my good Lorde, which art the faythfull louer of all them that loue thée, for thine infinit loue to vouchſafe to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and inflame my heart with the fyre of thy loue: that I may
<pb facs="tcp:21583:87"/>
loue thée from the bottome of my heart as I am bounde, and giue mée grace to followe that feruencie and deuotion, which thy deuout ſeruaunt Magdalen ſhewed, in caſting that ſwéete liquor vpon thy heade and féete: And that I maye alſo declare the ſame, in annoynting of thée ſpirituallye: That is, in belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng ſtedfaſtlye, in honouring and reuerencing duely thy diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and moſt holy humanitie, in workyng accordyng to my power, in the ſeruice of my neighbour, to ayde and helpe him, and to perſeuer in ſo doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the dayes of my lyfe.
<pb facs="tcp:21583:87"/>
That by theſe meanes in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge of that filthyneſſe and odious ſauour which my ſinnes haue vnto this tyme cauſed, I may render for the time to come, the ſwéete ſauour of good workes which may bée acceptable both vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée and others that ſhall ſée the ſame. Amen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:21583:88"/>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Inſidet in tardo regum rex Christus aſello:</l>
                        <l>Cui veſtem ac ramos plebs bona ſteruit ouans.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:88"/>
                  <head>The ſolemnitie in the receiuing of Chriſt into the citie of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem the ſunday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his paſsion.</head>
                  <head>¶ Poynts to meditate vpon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 How that the day folowing, that is to ſay, fyue dayes before that Chriſte the true Lambe ſhould be ſacrificed for vs in his paſſion, he would preſent hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in Ieruſalem, euen as the lawe commaunded of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Lambe, whiche ſo many dayes before it ſhoulde be ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed, was to be prepared.</p>
                  <p>And for to ſhewe his good
<pb facs="tcp:21583:89"/>
wyll and with what deſyre of mynde, he came to offer hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: he woulde therefore enter into Ieruſalem with that ioye and ſolemnitie as was ſhewed him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſyder with what deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ioye, the people at that tyme receiued their true king and Lorde, and the diuerſitie of ſeruice they ſhewed in honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him: as in dreſſyng the ſtréetes with bowes, and ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their garments before him in the waye, and prayſing him with ſonges.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Call to minde alſo howe that in the myddeſt of that feaſting
<pb facs="tcp:21583:89"/>
and ioye in whiche our Lorde went, when he ſawe the Citie of Ieruſalem, he ſhedde his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull teares, well knowing how farre contrarywiſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of fiue daies he was to bée handled of them, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing within him ſelfe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of that Citie, which he knew for their ſinnes ſhould be deſtroyed and brought to ruine. Conſider howe ſtraightwayes after his entring into the Citie, he went to viſite the Temple, out of the which he draue away them that prophaned the ſame with their marchandize in buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:90"/>
                     <head>The prayer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Adore and worſhip thée moſt louing Ieſu, true and eternal King of Heauen and earthe, to whom al adoration, honour and reuerence is due, for all the workes whiche liuing in thys worlde thou diddeſt with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull wyſedome and infinite charitie.</p>
                     <p>And ſpecially I giue thankes and praiſe to thée for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die good wyll, with which thou moſt innocent Lamb, knowing that thou ſhouldeſt be ſacrificed for the ſynnes of the worlde, wouldeſt a fewe dayes before
<pb facs="tcp:21583:90"/>
preſent thy ſelfe in Ieruſalem, entring into it with feaſte and triumphe, willyng thereby to declare thy chéerefulneſſe and moſte earneſt deſyre wherein thou cameſt to offer thy ſelf vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, whereon thou knew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt our life to depende: &amp; that in dying thou ſhouldeſt ouercome and triumph ouer death it ſelfe, hell, ſinne, and all other our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes. I beſéech thy immeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable bountie and goodneſſe, to gyue mée grace and ſtrength, willynglye and gladly to offer my ſelfe to ſuche daungers and trauele as ſhall behoue mée to ſuffer in this lyfe, for thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice:
<pb facs="tcp:21583:91"/>
and make me to deſpiſe for thy loue, all the prayſes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours with which this deceite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full world would deceiue me: euen as thoſe ſolemnities, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and honours, with whiche the people of Ieruſalem recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thée, did not let thée with great compaſſion to wéepe and lament, what time other ſang and made great ioy.</p>
                     <p>Let my chiefe care be to ſéeke thée, and haue a zeale to honour thée and thine eternall Father: ſéeing and conſidering that thy care, which aſſoone as thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt entred the citie, thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt by and by goe to viſite his
<pb facs="tcp:21583:91"/>
temple, and beholding that moſt feruent zeale of thine, in dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing oute of it all them that boughte and ſolde in the ſame, not contented that the houſe of prayer ſhoulde be ſo prophaned. I humbly therefore beſéeche thy diuine maieſtie, that thou driue out of my heart euery thing that may prophane or defile it, to the ende it maye reſt as thy temple and houſe of prayer, into the which thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt vouchſafe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and dwell. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Conuiuis fis Chriſte cibus, coena<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> refectis</l>
                        <l>Abluis ipſe pedes: tum loca ſola petis.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:92"/>
                  <head>Of the laſt Supper which Chriſt our Lorde made to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: there maye be theſe poyntes following to meditate vpon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 With howe great méekenes and humilitie the ſauiour of the world riſing from ſupper, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the féete of his Diſciples, and alſo of Iudas, and wyped them with the towell where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was gyrt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondarily, conſider of the entier loue which moued him to inſtitute that high Sacrament, in the which he gaue his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to eate his moſt ſacred bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:21583:93"/>
and precious blood to drinke, and willed it ſhoulde remayne in his Church, as the foode and conſolation of our ſoules.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, call to minde that heauenly leſſon which he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to his Diſciples, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and exhorting them and vs alſo, to humilitie, charitie, and patience, of the whiche ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues he gaue vs ſo liuely examples in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ende of his life here.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:93"/>
                     <head>
                        <figure/> The prayer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Geue thée thanks moſt ſwéete Ieſu with all my hart, for thy
<pb facs="tcp:21583:94"/>
marueilous humilitie in aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thy ſelfe to become as a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt to waſhe the féete of thy ſeruants. And alſo I prayſe and worſhip thée, for the ineſtimable benefite that thou diddeſt work for vs, in willing to continue with vs in thy moſt holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the whiche thy bleſſed body is verily conteined, for the foode and comfort of our ſoules.</p>
                     <p>I humbly beſéeche thy infinite clemencie &amp; pitie, to graunt me grace to folowe this example of ſo great humilitie: and that my vile condition neuer become proude, when I ſhall conſider and ſée thy maieſtie ſo humbled.
<pb facs="tcp:21583:94"/>
And vouchſafe alſo my gracious Lorde and Redéemer, to waſhe my féete: that is to ſay, the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes and naughtie paſſions of my ſoule: And giue me that loue and charitie which thou diddeſt ſo greatlye commende to thy Diſciples, that with pureneſſe of hart, and with ſuche inwarde cleanneſſe of minde as I am bounde, and as is acceptable to God, I may draw neare to this moſte ſwéete Sacrament, and participate aboundauntlye of thoſe effectes which it worketh in deuoute ſoules. Graunt me alſo, O celeſtiall Scholema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and euerlaſting wiſdome of
<pb facs="tcp:21583:95"/>
the father, that thy moſt bleſſed words may be imprinted in me, which thou didſt preach in this worlde, &amp; chiefly thoſe words of thy latter talke neare thy death béeing full of ſo great charitie &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation, with the which thou didſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the ſorowful minds of thy beloued Diſciples. And ſéeing thou haſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life more ſwete then the hony or hony combe, make my ſoule to taſt it, chiefly to delight in it, and alwayes to obay it: &amp; that by it, as by a moſt light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lanterne, I may ſée how to guide my ſelfe in all my wayes and works. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Ter prece ſollicitat patrem ſudat<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> pauet<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>:</l>
                        <l>Innocuas ſtringunt impia vinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a manus.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:96"/>
                  <head>Of the prayer in the garden, and apprehending of our Sauiour.</head>
                  <head>¶Poyntes to meditate therevpon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 How our ſauiour going into the garden, to which place he knew his enemies ſhould come for to apprehend him: with that inward ſorow and feare which for our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fréely his ſoule would féele, he fel downe flat on the grounde, &amp; with moſt great reuerence, he made his prayers thrée times to his father, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bitter cup which was prepared for him, myght paſſe away: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding
<pb facs="tcp:21583:96"/>
ſubmitted himſelfe alwayes to his fathers moſt godly will.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Howe that his affliction and anguiſhe increaſing, which wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly he receaued, cauſed hym at the laſt to ſweate droppes of blood, that fell vppon the earth: And beyng in this agony, there came downe an Angell from heauen to comfort him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 How that being moued with the burnyng deſyre of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, he went and met his enemyes in the face: and was content to be kiſſed of that trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour Iudas, and of the other to be taken and cruelly bounde, to be forſaken of his diſciples, and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:97"/>
brought to the houſe of Annas the Biſhop.</p>
                  <figure/>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:97"/>
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>BLeſſed be thou my Lorde and God, O Ieſu Chriſt, for that thine infinit mercy, that it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thée, for to harten and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs, to be aſſaulted thy ſelfe wyth ſuche extréeme feare and ſadnes. And thou being the glad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe and comforte of Angels, diddeſt take well in worth to be comforted of an Angell. I bleſſe and prayſe thée alſo for that thy feruent loue, that for to looſe the bondes of our ſinnes, and to ſet vs at true libertie, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt thy ſelfe to bée taken and bounde of thy enemyes ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully like a théefe. I beſéeche thy
<pb facs="tcp:21583:98"/>
infinite goodneſſe therefore that in mine afflictions, feare, and ſadneſſe, I may haue the grace alwayes to run vnto thée with moſt humble and deuout praier, ſubmitting my ſelfe wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy bleſſed handes: and that ſo to doe, may be my onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and helpe, ſéeing that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thée, vaine is the health and helpe, that any worldly creature can giue me. I beſéeche thée alſo moſt méeke Lambe, by that thy patience and gentleneſſe, which with hard cordes and ropes did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſuffer thy ſelfe to be bounde when thou waſt taken: that thou wilte vouchſafe to bynde
<pb facs="tcp:21583:98"/>
my ſoule, with the chaynes of thy loue, that I being looſed by thée from my ſinnes, and from my diſorderly affections, ſuffer not my ſelfe to bée anye more bound with them. And that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the diuell, the worlde, nor the fleſhe, may at any time ſeparate me from thy loue, ſeruice, and moſt bleſſed will and pleaſure. Amen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:21583:99"/>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Ad ſedes Annae rapitur Caifae<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> tribunal:</l>
                        <l>Hic tota inſultat nocte proterua oohors.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:99"/>
                  <head>How Chriſt was lèd to the houſe of Annas and Caiphas.</head>
                  <head>¶The poyntes to meditate.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 The blaſphemies and villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies which were ſpoken againſt our redéemer by thoſe wicked miniſters: the outrages, buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges and beatinges which he ſuffered when he was led from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> garden to Annas houſe, where he was firſt preſented.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider the great méekenes, humilitie and modeſtie, which ſhyned in our Sauiour whiles he ſtoode before the preſence of
<pb facs="tcp:21583:100"/>
that proude byſhoppe, and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to the demaundes of his doctrine and of his Diſciples: &amp; tooke ſo patiently thoſe reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtrokes and buffets.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 And after that, howe wyth like ſpite, cruell handeling, and ſhame, he was ledde to the houſe of Chaiphas, where they vſed muche ſcornings &amp; iniuries to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him: as in couering and blindfolding his bleſſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend face, ſpitting in it, and ſtriking it: ſo that he paſſed all that night without any reſt at all.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:100"/>
                     <head>
                        <figure/> ¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>I Render thankes and prayſes to thée, moſte louing Ieſu, for
<pb facs="tcp:21583:101"/>
thy inuincible patience, with which it pleaſed thée for vs moſt vyle ſinners, to beare and ſuffer ſo greate trauelles, paynes and iniuries, ſubmitting thy moſt bleſſed bodye to them that did beate it, and thy moſt reuerend bearde and heare, to them that dyd teare it, beſpit it and ſoyle it: and diddeſt not turne thine amiable face from them that did ſpitte in in. I do humbly beſéech thy goodnes for that thy inſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable patience ſake, with which thou ſufferedſt ſo many ſtrokes and beatinges without grudge or anger towardes thyne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: that thou wilt graunt me
<pb facs="tcp:21583:101"/>
ſtrength and patience, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all perſecutions and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which in this worlde are wrought againſt me, knowing that my ſinnes deſerued muche more.</p>
                     <p>And ſéeing that thou, O Lord, whoſe face the Angels deſyre to behold, waſt content to haue it defyled with their moſte fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye ſpettinges, and all for to beautifye our ſoules: graunte me grace not to regarde the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nityes of thys body, or of the world, but to care for the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of my ſoule, and the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of holy vertue, and the workes thereof: With which
<pb facs="tcp:21583:102"/>
I may ſéeme worthy to appeare before thy face, in that moſte happye kyngdome, where the true and perfecte beawtie is: And where they ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned and clothed in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that ſhall raygne with thée with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Turba furens instat trahit ad praeteria vinctum.</l>
                        <l>Ficta probare malo crimina teſte parat.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:103"/>
                  <head>How Chriſt our Redeemer was brought to Pilates houſe.</head>
                  <head>¶Poyntes to meditate vpon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Howe the frydaye morning thoſe wicked Iewes which ſo greatly deſired the death of him that was the giuer of life, came earely in the morning to the houſe of Caiphas where they left him, &amp; after they had made an end of their wicked councell, in the which they iudged hym worthy of death, they led hym to the houſe of Pilate, that hée might giue iudgement on him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider with howe great modeſtie our Lorde ſtoode in the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:103"/>
preſence of Pilate, &amp; with howe great humilytie he aunſwered to the thinges he demaunded of him, and woulde neyther excuſe nor defende himſelfe, agaynſt any falſe inditement or accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions layd to his charge.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider alſo ſpecially thoſe wordes of our redéemer which he ſpake to Pilate: that is, when he ſayde, my kingdome is not of this worlde: declaring by thoſe wordes, that albeit he were the true king of heauen and earth, he came not yet to reigne in the world, but to ſuffer paines and to die for the life and redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:104"/>
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>BLeſſed bée thou Kinge of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for thy ſo great humility, that being the vniuerſall iudge of the lyuing and the deade, it pleaſed thée ſo much to abaſe thy ſelfe to be led and to be iudged of an vniuſt iudge. Who although he knewe thy innocencie and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the enuie of thy perſecutours: yet he ſuffered himſelfe to bée peruerted and ouercome with worldly feare. All whiche thou diddeſt willingly ſuffer, without laying of any excuſe for thy ſelfe in any thing: ſo great was thy
<pb facs="tcp:21583:104"/>
deſire to gyue thy lyfe for the world vnto death, being moued thy ſelfe thereto, through thy paſſing loue and charitie.</p>
                     <p>I beſeeche thée, O Lorde, to cleanſe awaye from mee all wycked inclinations which I féele in my ſelfe, when I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my ſynnes and my greate imperfections: Where as thou being an innocent and voyde of all faultes, wouldeſt not excuſe thy ſelf of thoſe falſe and vniuſt accuſations whiche were layde againſt thée. And ſéeing thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt confeſſe that thy kingdome was not of this worlde, I pray thée by that pouertie and baſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:105"/>
in which thou being King of heauen wouldeſt liue vppon the earth: That thou wilte graunt me grace to diſpiſe the honour &amp; vaine fauour of thys worlde, and that I onely deſire and ſéeke for that true and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting kingdome, which thou haſt prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that truely and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue and ſerue thée. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Ductus ad Herodem cum nil reſpondeat, albam</l>
                        <l>Induitur chlamydem luditur, eijcitur.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:106"/>
                  <head>How Chriſt beeing ledde vnto Herodes houſe, was alſo there mocked &amp; ſcorned.</head>
                  <head>¶Poynts to meditate.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Call to minde the diligence and buſie crueltie of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers miniſters of iniquitie, in leading our Sauiour from Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to Herode, with their grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and inſatiable deſire to put him to death.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Remember alſo that cleare bright quiet countenaunce, and continuall ſilence, in the which our moſt méeke Sauiour ſtood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> before Herode, without anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:21583:106"/>
to any queſtion they made to him, becauſe they were al cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, vayne, and vnprofitable.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 How that béeing mocked and ſcorned of Herode and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he was apparrelled in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with a white garment: and then brought againe to Pilates houſe, with all the ſhame and reprochfull deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they could i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:107"/>
                     <head>
                        <figure/> ¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>I Moſte humbly adore and worſhip thée moſt benigne
<pb facs="tcp:21583:107"/>
Ieſu, for thoſe weariſome iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys which for our ſaluation it was thy will to make, béeing ſo many times led, hurried, and haled from one iudge to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: in which proceſſion thou didſt ſuffer ſuch gaſings, ſhame, and mockeries, namely, béeing clothed with that white garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thou waſt of all men mocked and ſcorned. How ſhal I be able O Lord, to anſwere theſe thy ſo great mercies and benefites re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued at thy godly hands: that being by the tranſgreſſion and diſobedience of our firſt father Adam, ſpoyled of that white gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of innocencie and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie
<pb facs="tcp:21583:108"/>
wherwith he was indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thou which art the ſecond A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, our moſt true and louing father, woldeſt recompence that loſſe and others which we had receiued of him, in béeing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be ſo clothed &amp; diſpiſed, beſides other great iniuries and tormentes whiche thou diddeſt ſuffer. I therfore beſech thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, for thy ſo gret trauels and rebukes, that thou wilt pardon me my euill and vnprofitable walkings which I haue made in the diſcourſe of my life, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the waye of perdition: and graunt me grace to runne cherefully from henceforth in
<pb facs="tcp:21583:108"/>
the way of thy holy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, &amp; perfect obſeruance of my calling and ſtate. So that I grudge not or diſdayne, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I be neuer ſo muche ſet at nought &amp; deſpiſed of men for thy loue, ſith that I ſée thée whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che art the wiſdome of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall father, with ſo great ſilence to holde thy peace, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be mocked and clothed like a foole, to recompence ſo my fooliſh pageantes and ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with which I haue ſo many times offended thée, from the which I pray thée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth to preſerue me. Amen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:21583:109"/>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Ex pedit hic virgas iudex &amp; verbera torquet:</l>
                        <l>Largifluo tellus, ſanguinis imbre madet.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:109"/>
                  <head>The ſcourging of Chriſt our Sauiour.</head>
                  <head>¶ Poyntes to meditate.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 How our Lorde béeing brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght agayne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Pilate, who thinking by giuing him ſome kind of puniſhment to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the rage of the Iewes that were very importune vpon him to put Chriſt to death: he tooke order he ſhuld be whipped.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider the ſharpneſſe and bitter crueltie of thoſe pityleſſe tormentors in ſcourging of that moſt méeke Lambe, in ſpoyling him of his garments, and bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him ſtrongly to a piller, and ſo to beate him without all
<pb facs="tcp:21583:110"/>
mercy and compaſſion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Remember alſo how cruelly he was whipt and beaten with roddes, ſo that there remayned no one part of his bleſſed body vnwounded nor vnbathed with blood, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the crowne of his head to the ſoles of his féete.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Adore &amp; worſhip, O my Lorde God, thy déepe iudgementes, which are worthy to be adored and magnified, and not ſerched. And amongſt other I worſhip and thanke thée, for that which ſufficeth to make the very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels them ſelues to maruell:
<pb facs="tcp:21583:110"/>
that thou béeing the beloued ſonne of the eternall Father, to whom all ſeruice and reuerence is due, and of whom it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that the whip ſhal not come neare to his tabernacle: diddeſt willingly conſent to be bounde naked to a piller, and ſo ſharply to be whipped and beaten, as if thou haddſt bene ſome vile ſlaue and vagabound: willing to pay with ſo ſharp ſtripes of thy vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin fleſhe, for the vayne and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous delightes that I thy vile ſlaue haue pampered my fleſhe withall, agaynſt thy will and pleaſure.</p>
                     <p>And ſéeing thou haſt vouchſafed
<pb facs="tcp:21583:111"/>
to defende me with thy ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſuffring them to be ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whipped: I beſéech thy infinit clemencie to kéepe far from me the ſcourge of thy wrath, the which I know to haue deſerued for the multitude of my ſinnes. And let this thy diſcipline teach me hereafter, and cauſe me to ſhake off all delicateneſſe and pleaſures in pampering of my fleſhe, by chaſtening and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of it by due penaunce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may not rebel any more agaynſt thée, and hinder me to attende vpon thy ſeruice as I am bound. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Spinea ſerta caput pangunt: illudit amictus</l>
                        <l>Purpureus, turbis ecce homo praetor ait.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:112"/>
                  <head>Of the crowning of Chriſt with thornes.</head>
                  <head>Matter for meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Howe thoſe tormentors bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wéerie of beating that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body, did looſe him from the piller, and howe our moſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Lorde did humbly gather vp his garmentes whiche they had caſte and ſcattered on the grounde, with the whiche he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered agayne his moſte ſacred body, béeing all bloody, ſore and full of payne.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider howe that hauing yet ſcantly put on his clothes,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:112"/>
the ſouldiers of Pilat were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to honor him in ſcorne, with royall enſignes, becauſe they ſayde, he had made him ſelfe a king, they clothed him with a red purple cape or mantell, and crowned his head with a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande of moſte ſharpe pricking thornes, and they put a réede in his hande in ſtead of a ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with which they ſtrake him, and kneling before him, in moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king they ſaluted him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Then alſo beholde howe Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late brought foorth in the ſight of all the people, the king of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, euen as he was ſo mocked and yll handled, thinking that
<pb facs="tcp:21583:113"/>
their obſtinate furie might be ſo pacified, when they ſhould ſée him in that caſe worthy of pitie and compaſſion. But it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſuffiſed them, but rather they cried the more, crucifie him.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:113"/>
                     <head>
                        <figure/> ¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>WHat thanks may I render to thée
<pb facs="tcp:21583:114"/>
O my God, that thou being the true king of heauen &amp; of earth, and ſo worſhipped and reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the Angels them ſelues, diddeſt not refuſe to beare that ſhamefull and painfull enſignes of a faygned King, with which thou waſte ſcorned and mocked of moſte vile men, neither yet diddeſt grudge to appeare open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in the ſight of all the people with that painefull ſharpe pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king crowne of thorne, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou waſt crowned of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom thou contrariwiſe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt to crowne with glory? And who would not maruell at their obſtinate malice, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they could
<pb facs="tcp:21583:114"/>
finde out ſo many inuentions, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more to put thée to ſhame, paine and torment? but more cauſe of maruell is in thy burning chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Lord, which the waters of ſo great tribulations and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were not able to quenche, no, nor in one poynt to coole.</p>
                     <p>And euen as thou waſt neuer ſatiſfyed, nor couldeſt thinke in thy ſelf to haue loued vs inough: ſo thou couldeſt neuer fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfye thy ſelfe in ſuffering for them whom thou louedſt. Let thy bountifull goodneſſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bée honoured and thanked of the Angels &amp; of all creatures, the which I doe alſo adore and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:115"/>
worſhip and deſire that I maye alwayes ſo doe with all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: humbly beſéeching thée, that thou wylte cauſe mée to knowe thy highneſſe &amp; almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie maieſtie, that I maye with truth and vnfaynedly, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally honour that ſame, &amp; to giue me grace that I may wyth the eyes of my ſoule beholde that lamentable ſpectacle and ſight, whiche Pilate ſhewed to the Iewes, in ſaying, beholde the man: That my hart being ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made tender and mollyfied, I maye haue the more compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and pitie of thée, and wyth more earneſt deſire loue thée, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21583:115"/>
embrace thée.</p>
                     <p>And alſo to reioyce in my ſelfe to be reuiled and diſpiſed in the world for thy ſake according to thine example, hoping after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes through thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye to be crowned of thée in heauen. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Inſons damnatur, tandem portare iubetur</l>
                        <l>Proh dolor, ipſe ſuae pondera ſaeua crucis.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:116"/>
                  <head>Howe Chriſt caried the Croſſe to be crucified: and the poynts to meditate thereon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Howe Pilate beyng weryed with the importune calling and cryinges on of the Iewes, did iudge Chriſt the author and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of life to death: whoſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he willingly accepted, for the great deſire he had to worke our ſaluation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſyder with howe great humilitie, he did beare that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uye trée of the Croſſe vppon his ſhoulders: Which for that it was ſo huge and great, made hym often tymes to fall to the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:117"/>
grounde, and ſo to renewe his gréeuous paines.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider alſo that being not well able to goe for his weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mightie burthen, they tooke the croſſe of his ſhoulders and cauſed Cirineus to beare it. And howe hée turned himſelfe to comfort and admoniſhe the deuout women, who with great compaſſion followed hym wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: Where you maye call to mynde what ſorrowe his bleſſed mother ſuffered when ſhée ſawe this lamentable ſight.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>WHo woulde not bée amaſed, O moſte ſwéete Ieſu, of the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:117"/>
bottomleſſe fountain of thy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing humilitie, that beeing the iudge of the liuing and the dead, to whome by thy heauenlye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all iudgement was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: wouldeſt ſubmitte thy ſelfe to bée iudged of a mortall man, being an vniuſt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon, thou being moſt innocent and cleare from al ſin, and to accepte with great obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience &amp; méekenes the ſentence of death which malefactours de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, that by death they might obtaine life. I render vnto thée infinite thankes as wel for this incomparable charitie, as alſo for that good will and readineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21583:118"/>
with the which as it were an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iſaac, thou cariedſt on thy backe, the wood wherewith thou ſhouldeſt be ſacrificed in the fire of thy moſt burning charity: wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling thereby to make ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the iuſtice of thine eternal father for our ſinnes which thou bareſt on the croſſe. And ſéeyng that in accepting the ſentence of death which Pylate pronounced againſt thée, thou deſeruedſt that the ſentence of eternall death ſhoulde be reuoked whiche was pronounced againſt me: therfore I humbly beſéech thée of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie to defend &amp; kéepe mée, that I deſerue not to léeſe this ſo great
<pb facs="tcp:21583:118"/>
priuiledge of grace, &amp; to incurre by my ſinfulnes, into the ſame ſentence of damnation, from the which for thy part thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered mée. Geue mée alſo the grace and ſtrength to bée al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes able to followe thée in bearing of my croſſe according as thou haſte commaunded vs: that is to ſay, the trauels &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation which it ſhall pleaſe thée to lay vppon me in this life. The which for good cauſe maye be eaſie and light vnto me: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the paine and trouble thou diddeſt féele, in bearing ſo willingly for my loue thy croſſe. Amen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:21583:119"/>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Crux recipit feſſum, claui palmaſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> pedeſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>
                        </l>
                        <l>Traijciunt, ſedant fellea vinaſitim.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:119"/>
                  <head>Of the nayling of Chriſt vpon the Croſſe, ye may meditate theſe poyntes.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Howe that being with great trouble and trauell nowe come to the mount of Caluarie which was the place where the male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours ſhoulde put him to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, in ſteade of good wyne which they vſed to geue others that went to their ſorrowfull death to comfort their ſpirites, they gaue Chriſt wine that was myxte with gall, becauſe there ſhoulde no member or part, nor yet anye ſenſe remayne in him without torment.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:120"/>2 Remember the inhumanitie of them to ſpoyle him of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, which was a new cauſe of griefe and torment to that moſt méeke Lambe, and a renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the excéeding ſorrowes which he ſuffered. And likewiſe call to minde howe that béeyng ſpoyled of his garmentes, hée ſtoode all naked, in moſt bytter ſorrowes, griefe and ſhame.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Then further conſider, with howe great crueltie they cauſed hym to bée ſtretched vppon that harde bedde of the Croſſe, which they had prepared for him: On the which they perced throughe and nayled with bygge groſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21583:120"/>
nayles, the moſt holy hands and féete of him, that made bothe heauen and earth. And on the other ſyde conſyder wyth what excéedyng patience and charitie hée ſuffered ſo great tormentes as no tongue ſuffyceth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>NO tongue moſt mercifull Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, ſufficeth to giue thankes and prayſe worthye to thée, for thy burning charity, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thée with ſo great patience to beare and ſuffer the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable tormentes thou diddeſt
<pb facs="tcp:21583:121"/>
féele, what tyme thou waſt nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the Croſſe.</p>
                     <p>For albeit the griefe &amp; ſmart of thy paine and ſorrowe were excéedyng great: yet without all compariſon muche more paſſing great and vnſpeakable was the greatneſſe of thy loue that prycked thée forwarde to ſuffer it.</p>
                     <p>Thy verie works, O Lorde, prayſe thée, and for my parte I thanke and praiſe thée, as much as I maye, confeſſing my ſelfe neuer to be able to thanke thée for the leaſt parte of that I am bounde vnto thée.</p>
                     <p>And therefore I praye the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:121"/>
for thoſe moſte bitter ſorowes and for the entier loue of thine, which cauſed thée for the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the worlde to ſuffer ſo gréeuous tormentes: that thou wilt graunt me grace that they maye be alwayes fixed in my harte and minde as the percing arrowes of thy tender loue, and that renouncing all vayne loue of this worlde, I maye be ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nayled and faſtened to thée in perfect loue and obedience. And for ſo muche as thou art figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by that cluſter of grapes whiche the two men broughte on a ſtaffe vppon their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from the lande of promiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:122"/>
and waſte troden foorth in that wine preſſe of the Croſſe, that out of thée ſhould flowe moſte ſwéete wine to ſwéeten and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome our ſoules: ſwéeten and fil my ſoule with that wine which cauſeth men to become chaſt and pure.</p>
                     <p>And cauſe that I be faſt nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with thée, with the nayles of thy loue and charitie. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly nayle my fleſhe with the feare of thée, that it be not rebellious agaynſt the ſpirite: and let my hands and féete be ſo nayled with thine, that they neither moue nor ſtretche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thy bleſſed will. And geue
<pb facs="tcp:21583:122"/>
me ſo abundant grace, that I may be deſirous to ſuffer, and to be diſprayſed of all men for thée, and to be preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed downe for thy diuine loue. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Conſpicitur crux alma, ſolo caelo<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> verenda:</l>
                        <l>In qua expirauit mox viriuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> parens.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:123"/>
                  <head>How Chriſt was exalted vpon the Croſſe.</head>
                  <head>¶ Poynts to meditate vpon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 How that béeing in maner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaide with ſuch exceſſiue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and outcryes of the people nayled vpon the croſſe, he was exalted or lifted vp on high, that all men might beholde him. And was put in the place appoynted betwene two théeues that were alſo crucified with him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Remember the incomparable ſorowe and anguiſhe which his moſte bleſſed mother felt, when ſhe ſaw her ſwéete ſonne woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from toppe to toe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed ſo muche through the
<pb facs="tcp:21583:124"/>
ſtripes and torments receiued, that ſcarcely ſhe might knowe her owne childe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Call to minde alſo howe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo many tormentes as our moſt mercifull ſauiour ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, the firſt wordes he ſpake béeing nayled vpon the Croſſe, was to pray for his very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and them that crucified him, whoſe blindnes and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie gréeued him more then his owne paynes and torments.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Confeſſe, my moſt ſwéet Lord and true louer of mankinde,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:124"/>
that in all the time of my life, if I ſhould do none other thing els both day and night, yet I could not worthily for my part prayſe and bleſſe thée, for this vniuerſall benefite of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of mankinde, both yll conſidered of me &amp; many other. What may I then ſay, O eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall loue of the father, ſéeing thée in our mortall fleſh ſo aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for my ſake, tormented for me, and lifted vp vpon the croſſe in the middeſt of two théeues, and as one of them, and muche worſe handled?</p>
                     <p>O my Lord thanks be giuen to thée of all men, and of all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb facs="tcp:21583:125"/>
for thine infinite charitie the which is ſufficient to make them all to maruell, ſéeing that I am he which hath committed the robbery, and yet it is thy pleaſure to ſuffer the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due therefore.</p>
                     <p>I beſéech thée O infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſéeing it hath pleaſed thée to paye for mine iniquitie and ſinnes, and that thou haſte pardoned me thoſe whiche I haue committed: that thou wilt giue me grace to take héede that I treſpaſſe not in the like of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences hereafter, and that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue not eternall tormentes, from whiche by meanes of thy
<pb facs="tcp:21583:125"/>
tormentes thou haſte ſo manye times deliuered me. Giue me O Lorde, the grace that I maye ſtande and ſtaye my ſelfe ſurely and conſtantly by thy Croſſe with thy moſte bleſſed mother, féeling ſome part of the ſorowe that ſhe felt.</p>
                     <p>And giue mine eyes grace to looke vp vpon thée rayſed and lifted on high vpon the Croſſe, ſo that I maye be holpen from my ſpirituall ſoares, as they were holpen from their corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſoares, who did beholde the ſerpent that Moyſes did in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of thée exalt in the deſart. Vouchſafe alſo to graunt me ſo
<pb facs="tcp:21583:126"/>
much thy fauour and grace, that I maye reſte my ſelfe vnder the ſhadow of this trée of life, and that I maye taſte of his moſte ſwéete fruite, the whiche maye cauſe me to loue euen mine enemies, and to pray for them: euen as thou ſtanding nayled vpon the ſame trée, as it were from thy chayre and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, doeſt teach and preach vnto me. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Exanimum pectus transfigit cuſpide miles:</l>
                        <l>Pectore ab effoſſo lympha cruor<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> fluunt.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:127"/>
                  <head>How Chriſt was thruſt into the ſide with a ſpeare.</head>
                  <head>¶ Poyntes to meditate.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 When that wicked genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had nailed and lifted vp the redéemer of the world vpon the croſſe, and coulde not nowe any more ſtrike him with their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, they ſmote him with their tongs with many reprochefull words and blaſphemies, giuing him vineger to drinke in his great thirſt vpon a ſponge.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider alſo how after the other words which he ſpake, in promiſing the thiefe Paradiſe which committed himſelfe vnto him, and giuing S. Iohn to his
<pb facs="tcp:21583:127"/>
mother in ſtead of her ſonne, &amp; in him alſo vs, and her to Iohn, and likewiſe to vs, to be as a mother: and declaring the gret thirſt whiche he had, and that chiefly was for our ſaluation: he then finally commended his ſpirite into the handes of his eternall father, and ſo inclining downe his head he yelded vp the ghoſt. Of whoſe tormentes and death the heauens declare they did in ſome part féele the griefe: for the ſunne was eclipſed, the earth trembled, the very ſtones ſheuered in péeces, the graues opened, the veyle of the temple deuided.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:128"/>3 Conſider alſo the cruel launce and thruſting in of the ſpeare, with the whiche Longinus ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a gappe into the ſyde of Chriſt, out of the which iſſued blood and water. And albeit to him it was no payne, becauſe he was already deade, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his moſt innocent mother felte it, whoſe bowels and hart was in thoſe moſt gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſorowes and ſighes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and thruſt through: agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the propheſie of Simeon.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:128"/>
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>I Render vnto thée, O Ieſu Chriſt moſt high and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Biſhop, infinite thankes, for that thou haſt offred thy ſelf to thy father in moſte ſwéete ſacrifice, and brought vnto an ende the works of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thou diddſt take vpon thée, neuer ſtaying therein neither for moſte bitter tormentes which they put thee too, nor yet for the multitude of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies they ſpake agaynſt thee. For the whiche I humblye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech thee, that thou vouchſafe to open the eyes of my ſoule, that I may beholde and ſee, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb facs="tcp:21583:129"/>
marke that whiche thou haſt wrought and taught on the croſſe and in thy death. Bring low, O Lord, my hawtines and pride, in ſéeing thy head incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and brought lowe, vnder a crowne of thorne. Temper and moderate my gluttonie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancie, with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thy moſt ſwete mouth taſting the bitter gawle and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger. Cauſe me to forſake the delites of the fleſh: in ſéeing thy fleſh put to ſo great paynes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the croſſe. Mollifie the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of my hart, and ſuffer it not to be more hard then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtones, which ſhiuered in péeces at thy
<pb facs="tcp:21583:129"/>
death, Make me, O Lord, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into thy open ſide, where I may more ſafely ſaue my ſelfe in the great and perillous flood of this world, then in the arke of Noe. Cauſe me for thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice willingly to endure &amp; beare all trouble and aduerſitie, ſeing that thou for my ſake wouldeſt giue thy moſt bleſſed life: and euen as thou diddeſt perſeuer and continue vnto death in the obedience of thy father, ſo graunt that I maye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways perſeuer in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience towards thée. Amen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:21583:130"/>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Ex cruce traiectos artus &amp; frigida membra</l>
                        <l>Detrahit, alta animi vis pietaſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> virum.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:130"/>
                  <head>How our Redeemer was taken downe from the Croſſe.</head>
                  <head>¶The poynts of meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 How the rage of that vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie generation being partly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate &amp; quieted with the death of him that is the life of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world they returned into the citie: but his moſt afflicted mother conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued with him, accompanied with the beloued diſciple Iohn, and other deuoute women, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying to ſée if they might by any meanes burie him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Call to remembrance howe thoſe honorable perſonages, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph and Nicodemus, hauing leaue of Pilate to take Chriſte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, brought oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts
<pb facs="tcp:21583:131"/>
and other things neceſſarie for to embalme and burie him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider alſo with how great deuotion, reuerence, and tears, they tooke him from the croſſe: and howe deſirous his vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table mother was to take him in hir armes, &amp; to imbrace him.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>I Adore and worſhip thée my moſt louing ſauior, I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k thee and prayſe thée with all my hart &amp; power: for that through thy moſt holy croſſe thou haſte recouered and ſaued the world. All thy workes, O Lorde, are moſt perfect, and ſo it was thy will and pleaſure perfectly to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe
<pb facs="tcp:21583:131"/>
this worke of ſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of our redemption, not leauing any thing that was to be done or ſuffered, of that which of thine infinite wiſdome was ordeined, and of thy holy Prophetes foreſpoken, which in thoſe words thou diddeſt ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: It is iuſtified: whiche thou ſpakeſt a litle before thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt vp the ghoſt.</p>
                     <p>Thanks be alſo to thy diuine power and might, with which dying thou haſt deſtroyed death, after the maner of that ſtrong Sampſon, with thy death thou haſt ouercome thine enemies. I beſéeche thee therefore which
<pb facs="tcp:21583:132"/>
art the giuer of life, by the ſame thy deth, that mortifying all my concupiſcences and diſorderly affections, thou wilt reuiue my ſoule with the life of thy grace, and ſo make me dye to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayne pleaſures, honours, and deſires of the world &amp; of the fleſhe, that it may liue onely to thée, onely confeſſe thée, adore and worſhip thée, dwel in thée, &amp; ſeke for thoſe things which belong to thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: as thoſe thy deuoute ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants did in taking of thée from the croſſe, &amp; honoring thy moſte bleſſed body in procuring to burie it, being ſo greatly diſhonored before. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Hic complexa ſinu corpus miſerabile nati</l>
                        <l>Virgo parens lachrymis vulnera ſacra vigat.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:133"/>
                  <head>How our Sauiour beeing nowe taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe, was layd in his moſte ſorowfull mothers lappe.</head>
                  <head>¶ Poyntes to meditate.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt conſider with how gret tendernes the moſt bleſſed vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin mother receiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead body of her ſwéete ſonne béeing nowe taken from the croſſe, &amp; behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding particulerly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignes of his ſoares and wounds, with moſte tender loue ſhe kiſſed the ſame, embraced &amp; bathed it with the teares which abundantly iſſued out of her pitifull eyes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Then cal to mind the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table words which his mother
<pb facs="tcp:21583:133"/>
ſpake, when ſhe ſaw that bleſſed body of his ſo ſcourged, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ill handled, the which ſhe with ſo great loue and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence had brought vp, whoſe words &amp; ſighes were inough to breake with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion the hart of any that heard them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Remember alſo the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble playnt which other deuoute men &amp; women made that were there preſent, and chiefly of that welbeloued diſciple Iohn, and Magdalen which helde &amp; clipped faſt the féete of her ſwéete ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, not ſatiſfying her ſelfe y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in kiſſing and waſhing them with her pitifull teares.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:134"/>
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> My moſt merciful father and my god, who ſhal giue water to my head, and a fountayne of teares to mine eyes, that I may bewayle the paynefull death of my ſwéet redéemer both day and night, &amp; celebrate his holy exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies together with that deuout companie whiche with wofull playnt did celebrate the ſame? Or who may giue me an hoate burning hart worthily to praiſe thée, and thanke thée for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable benefite which thou haſt done for me, in that thou haſte vouchſafed that thine onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne ſhould léeſe his life
<pb facs="tcp:21583:134"/>
to giue me life? Whom would it not amaſe to ſée this thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable charity, that for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme a vile ſlaue, wouldeſt giue to death thy dearly beloued ſon? All the Angelicall ſpirites do laude &amp; prayſe thée, ſo that I nor all men in the world know nor yet are able to thanke thée, nor yet vnderſtand thy ſo gret mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And becauſe I haue no tong able to do it, as it ought to be, I pray thée of thine infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to graunt me an heart that may take compaſſion and féele in part that which thy moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mother felt, when ſhe beheld and ſaw thoſe gréeuous wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds
<pb facs="tcp:21583:135"/>
and ſcourgings of her and thy moſt louing ſonne. Geue me therfore, O Lorde, teares in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, that I may bewayle with her his death, &amp; alſo wéepe for that which was the occaſion therof, and that was my ſinnes, the which I pray thée for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thy ſonnes ſake, that thou wilt pardon me, and for the time to come to preſerue me, that I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend not in the ſame agayne, but alwayes hate and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre my ſinnes and wickedneſſe. Amen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:21583:135"/>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Et florum nimbo, fuſiſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> lignoribus vngunt:</l>
                        <l>Vncta<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> candenti ſindone membra tegunt.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:136"/>
                  <head>How the bleſſed body of Chriſt was anoynted and dreſſed to the buriall.</head>
                  <head>Meditations thereof.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 When night drew neare, S. Iohn, Ioſeph, and Nicodemus, (as it maye be godly thought) prayed our Lady to geue them leaue to annoynt the moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body of her ſonne: who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréed to their godly requeſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit that ſhe vnderſtoode that there was an other principall annointing, that is, that he was annointed of his diuinitie, with the which he was vnited.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider with what great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion
<pb facs="tcp:21583:136"/>
and reuerence that moſt diuine body was anoynted, and how many ſighes &amp; teares they ſhed euery one that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereat, in ſéeing him ſo wounded and pitifully handled, and ſpecially beholding thoſe fiue principall wounds worthy of ſo great compaſſion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider that when the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body was annoynted, they decently wounde it in a white ſhéete they brought with them, and couering his ſaid body with a fine launde, ſo ſhrowde it vp to be buried, according to the maner of the Iewes.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:21583:137"/>
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>MY ſoule bleſſeth thée, O moſt louing Ieſu, and all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers within me geue thankes &amp; prayſe to thy moſt holy name for all thy works, which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to be moſt worthy of all prayſe and bleſſings: But ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally I prayſe and magnifie thée, for that thou haſt accompliſhed and finiſhed that ſo highe and heauenly worke of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on whiche my ſaluation and life dependeth. I alſo adore and worſhip thy precious body, with the which it hath pleaſed thée to ſuffer moſt gréeuous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb facs="tcp:21583:137"/>
and ſeing thou my Lord and God waſt content to accept that deuotion and pietie of thy frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, that came to do thée their ſeruices, and waſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent being dead, that thy body ſhould be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted with thoſe materiall oyntments which they brought, of the which thou hadſt no néede at all, becauſe thou waſt preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from all corruption with the ſwéete balme of thy diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. I beſéeche thy clemencie, that thou vouchſafe to graunt me that pietie, that charitie, and thoſe teares of deuotion, that I may be able to annoynt thee ſpirituallye, whiche is
<pb facs="tcp:21583:138"/>
the vnction that is wonte to bée moſt acceptable to thy maieſtie.</p>
                     <p>Vouchſafe alſo my Sauiour, to imprint in myne heart thoſe fiue moſt holy woundes, whiche maye bée at all tymes my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, my medicine, the tower of my fortreſſe, my refuge &amp; ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie more ſure and ſafe, then thoſe Cityes whiche in the olde lawe were appoynted for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders to runne vnto and ſaue them ſelues: And that by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of them I maye eſcape, what tyme it ſhall pleaſe thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine iuſtice to puniſh me for my ſinnes. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Conditur, ah, tumulo mundi mihi conditor in quo</l>
                        <l>Vnicaſpes hominum conditur vnaſalus.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:139"/>
                  <head>Howe Chriſt was put into the graue.</head>
                  <head>Matters of meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Howe that moſt ſacred body was caried &amp; put with due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of Ioſeph in a newe ſepulchre or graue, the which was nere to the place where he was crucified. And here you may call to minde alſo the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſighes and abundance of teares of his moſt ſorrowfull mother, and of thoſe holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that were there preſent.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider the extreme pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the king of heauen and of earth, who when he was dead, had not any place where to reſt
<pb facs="tcp:21583:139"/>
his head, but after death was buried in the ſepulchre or bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of an other.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Then finally conſider howe loth and gréeuous that ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mother was, to depart from the ſepulchre where her treſure was left and layde, and the dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſolate ſadneſſe ſhe felt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelfe depriued from his ioyful company, vntil his riſing agayne, whiche ſhe looked for with a ſtedfaſt fayth.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>AL thy works, O my God and lord Chriſt Ieſu, be holy, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, &amp; wrought by infinite wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which without ende
<pb facs="tcp:21583:140"/>
I laude, giue thankes &amp; prayſes to thée, and ſpecially for thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſion, death and buryall.</p>
                     <p>For euen as when the worke of the creation of the worlde was finiſhed, the ſcripture ſaith thou diddeſt reſt and ceaſſe from crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting anye more thinges: ſo alſo now the great worke of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of man béeyng alſo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, thou tookeſt thy reſt and dyddeſt ceaſſe from ſuffering a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, and wouldeſt that thy bleſſed body vnited with thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, ſhoulde remayne cloſed within the ſepulcher: thy moſte bleſſed ſoule vnited with the ſame Diuinitie, in meane time
<pb facs="tcp:21583:140"/>
diſcending to viſite and comfort with thy preſence &amp; glory, thoſe holy fathers thy great friendes, the which with vnſpeakable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire looked for that day.</p>
                     <p>Bleſſed and prayſed for euer be thyne infinite mercie, power and wiſedome: the which ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth ouer all, and diſpoſeth all thinges ſwéetely. For the which I praye thee to open the eyes of my ſoule, that I may learne to know, loue and reuerence thée. Geue mée alſo my redéemer, plentie of teares of compaſſion with the which I maye accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie thy moſte ſorrowfull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who at this tyme remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:21583:141"/>
ſole and deſolate beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with great affection which ſhée felte for thy death and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, vnto the time that thou cameſt agayne to wype awaye thoſe pitifull teares which ran downe her reuerende face. I deſyre alſo and praye thée to graunt me a cleane harte, voide of all corruption of ſinne, where as in the lyke Sepulcher, not of harde ſtone, but of tender fleſhe and louynge, it may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light thée to reſt, vntyll the time thou vouchſafe of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to bring mée eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſt. Amen.</p>
                     <figure/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Mortis victor adeſt, animis comitatus ab orco,</l>
                        <l>Ne tumulo hanc matres quaerite, vinus abit.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21583:142"/>
                  <head>The glorious reſurrection of Chriſt our Sauiour.</head>
                  <head>¶Poyntes to meditate vpon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt conſider how that when the moſt bleſſed ſoule of Chriſte had béen in <hi>Lymbo</hi> &amp; comforted thoſe holy fathers, and brought them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence: the ſonday mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it did returne againe and vnite it ſelfe with his moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bodye, &amp; cauſed it to become glorious, reſplendent, immortal and impaſſible, and ſo with the diuine power, &amp; thoſe glorious indowme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which it communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the body, it roſe vp out of the place where it lay, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher or graue remaining faſt
<pb facs="tcp:21583:142"/>
ſhut and cloſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Ye may alſo thinke, that the firſt thing he did, being raiſed from death, was to viſite his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued mother, which with ſo many teares, ſighes &amp; ſorowes, miſſed him and looked for him. All which griefes were turned into incomparable ioyes &amp; glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, with the glorious ſight of her ſonne, raiſed agayne from death to life.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Ye may alſo meditate howe he firſte appeared vnto Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len before the other, who when ſhe knew him, ſhe was greatly comforted: and likewiſe vppon his other apparitions as vpon
<pb facs="tcp:21583:143"/>
this daye, as when he ſhewed himſelfe and appeared to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute women which went to the ſepulcher, and after to his Diſciples goyng towardes the caſtle of Emans.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>¶ The prayer.</head>
                     <p>THy name be bleſſed without end, moſt ſwéete Ieſu my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer, for that after the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt of thy paſſion, there is come the faire bright day of thy glory: &amp; to the night of ſorrowes and teares for thy death, the feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall &amp; ioyful day of thy reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth ſuccéede. For the one &amp; for the other, I giue prayſe and thanks to thée, as for the one and
<pb facs="tcp:21583:143"/>
for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other I am debtour to thée: bicauſe thou wouldeſt dy for my ſinnes &amp; riſe again for our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. And therefore it is iuſt, that they which do ſuffer &amp; wepe with thée in thy ſorowfull paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and death, ſhould alſo in thy gloryous reſurrection reioyce with thée &amp; thy moſt bleſſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Who according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure of hir anguiſhe &amp; ſorrowes paſſed, hath receiued the ioyes &amp; conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this day preſent. And what tongue may ſuffice to expreſſe that vnſpeakeable glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which hir hart felt, when ſhe ſawe thy glorious riſyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and the darkneſſe of thy
<pb facs="tcp:21583:144"/>
paſſion, turned into ſuch beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full clereneſſe, thy ſhames &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches into glory, thy wounds into ſuch beautie &amp; brightneſſe? When ſhe did conſider that now the ſtormy winter of thy perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions was paſt, &amp; the waters of the fludde of thy ſorows ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; that there ſhould be nowe no more Phariſies to accuſe thée nor Iudaſſes to betray thée, nor Pilates to iudge or condemne thée, nor death to haue might &amp; power ouer thée? If Iacob did ſo muche reioyce when hée vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that his ſonne Ioſeph who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he beleued to be dead, was a liue and did rule ouer all Egipt: how
<pb facs="tcp:21583:144"/>
great may we thinke the ioy of thy glorious mother to be, when hauing ſene thée dead, yea and of ſuch a death, did ſée thée alyue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, a vanquiſher of death, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing ouer the diuell &amp; hell, Lorde of heauen and of earth? wherefore I beſéech thée my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly king, that I calling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance this great triumph &amp; gladnes of thy bleſſed mother, thou wilt giue me grace to hate all other vaine pleaſures and worldly conſolations, whiche may ſeparate me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thée. Grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me Lord I pray thée by thy holy reſurrection, that my ſoule may riſe againe with thée, by the life
<pb facs="tcp:21583:145"/>
grace, and that I dye no more by the death of ſinne: ſo that I may by thy mercy hereafter riſe agayne glorious in body and ſoule, and come to reigne with thée eternally in glory. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Laude, Honour, and Glory, be for euer to Ieſu Chriſt our Redéemer, which ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, dyed, and roſe agayne. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21583:145"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
